<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story</id>
    <title>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-04-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story"/>
    <subtitle>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[1. From Curitiba to Provo]]></title>
        <id>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo</id>
        <link href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo"/>
        <updated>2024-04-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="university-or-college-both">University or college? Both!<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#university-or-college-both" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to University or college? Both!" title="Direct link to University or college? Both!">​</a></h2>
<p>In late 2005, at the age of 17, I took the entrance exams for music production at the <a href="https://ufpr.br/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Federal University of Paraná</a> (UFPR) and for music composition and conducting at the state's <a href="https://embap.curitiba1.unespar.edu.br/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">College of Music and Fine Arts</a> (Belas). I really only cared about the program at Belas, whose conservatory I'd already been attending since I was 10, but my parents and my school teachers expected me to apply to UFPR because it was the most prestigious university in the city.</p>
<p>I passed the exams with flying colours and enrolled in both programs simultaneously.</p>
<p>During the day, I attended UFPR. I felt impressed by my professors' credentials, most of whom had earned their terminal degrees and made a name for themselves in the US and Europe. Still, lectures were three-hour-long information dumps and the practical labs were a little too crowded to be useful. I enjoyed parts of it, such as socializing with like-minded people, but exams were hard and I struggled academically.</p>
<p>When my day at UFPR ended, I bussed downtown to Belas, where college courses were held in the evening. I remember some things about those classes vividly.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="video-game-music">Video game music<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#video-game-music" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Video game music" title="Direct link to Video game music">​</a></h3>
<p>One instructor asked us about our long-term goals. "I want to write music for video games," I replied. Everyone chuckled, thinking I was joking. "Oh, you're serious...," the instructor realized. I was. I knew it was a viable career choice, even then. I wasn't offended by their laughing, though; my answer was unusual for the time and place and laughing was a fair reaction. Besides, I've always enjoyed making people laugh, regardless of the reason.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="così-piangendo-va"><em>Così piangendo va</em><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#cos%C3%AC-piangendo-va" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to così-piangendo-va" title="Direct link to così-piangendo-va">​</a></h3>
<p>Another instructor, who taught counterpoint, had us listen to and analyze Victoria's <a href="https://youtu.be/9xPh-fXYAc4?si=BvWIHRapQ_IhjSPp" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>O magnum mysterium</em></a>. I had <strong>never</strong> heard anything like that. It moved me to tears. I would have similar experiences later in life with the final movement of Mozart's <a href="https://youtu.be/UsNk-7j9lpY?si=Urm8cFJn8IGiyObl&amp;t=1588" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"Jupiter" Symphony</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/dkfVzCZ68_Q?si=WMq4gcyNpIRFHNVd" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Mille regretz</em></a> by Josquin des Prez, and some of Monteverdi's <a href="https://youtu.be/YUgIJ212IVg?si=A0skWk9NgEqHSxVX" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">madrigals</a>. Come to think of it, beautiful music has made me cry much more as an adult than sadness.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nightly-commutes">Nightly commutes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#nightly-commutes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nightly commutes" title="Direct link to Nightly commutes">​</a></h3>
<p>After classes ended at about 22:30, I bussed back home with my best friend from church, who was a first-year student at Belas like me. Despite the late hour, buses were bustling with people who also had night classes in nearby colleges. It was a vibrant atmosphere, and my friend and I had some of the most fun conversations I've ever had in those commutes.</p>
<p>I felt fortunate to have a friend like him, with whom I could connect deeply on many levels. Our paths would diverge in later years, and I was never to regain a friendship like that in my adult life.</p>
<p>My home was seven blocks away from the bus stop. I was often accosted by aggressive stray dogs on the way that late at night. I think they felt territorial because the streets were deserted and they were after females in heat. I soon learned that they'd leave me alone if I threw rocks at them, so I always picked up some as soon as I got off the bus. I had to run a few times, but I was never bitten.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="provo-bound">Provo-bound<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#provo-bound" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Provo-bound" title="Direct link to Provo-bound">​</a></h2>
<p>Studying in two different institutions was unsustainable. Thankfully, it didn't last long.</p>
<p>Most of my adult cousins were attending <a href="https://www.byu.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brigham Young University</a> (BYU) at the time, and my parents thought I should too. At first, I resisted the idea, but they convinced me that going abroad would give me the best chance to succeed as a musician, and I acceded.</p>
<p>While I was a student of UFPR and Belas, I also had to scramble to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Prepare for and take an English proficiency test.</li>
<li>Record myself playing some piano pieces for my portfolio.</li>
<li>Schedule the ecclesiastical interviews BYU required.</li>
<li>Fill the application form and write essays about my background and merits.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn't know that the school year in the Northern Hemisphere was different than ours in Brazil, so I completed my application months after the deadline had passed. I applied so late that BYU had already sent out decision notifications by the time they received my application package.</p>
<p>Yet, somehow, I was admitted to start in the fall of that same year. My father maintains that this was only possible due to the intercession of an old family friend who knew someone in the admissions office. I think my father overestimates the pull this family friend had, but whatever the case, I got in.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="things-i-didnt-know">Things I didn't know<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#things-i-didnt-know" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Things I didn't know" title="Direct link to Things I didn't know">​</a></h3>
<p>In August 2006, I quit my studies in Curitiba and went to Provo with my mother. With the help of my cousins, I rented a shared room a few blocks away from campus. My mother helped me furnish whatever little space I had, and some days later she went back home.</p>
<p>That first year at BYU was very confusing. I understood little about what was happening.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>I didn't know that I had to register for courses and that I had to coordinate them so they wouldn't overlap with each other or with my work schedule. I also didn't know I had to plan how my courses would fulfill university-wide and program-specific requirements. Brazilian universities assigned all students the same course schedule.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I didn't know that applying to the university major I wanted—music theory and composition—was a separate process from applying to the university itself. That was an unwelcome surprise.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I didn't know any of the higher-ed lingo, e.g., undergraduate vs. graduate, and I didn't understand how these words related to my reality. I also didn't know the difference between teaching assistants (TAs), adjunct faculty, and full-time professors, and addressed everyone by the title of "Dr."</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>All I knew was that my family expected me to get good marks, qualify for merit-based bursaries, find a part-time job, and leave on a mission for <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints</a> the following year. That was the path my cousins had blazed for me.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-first-jobs">My first jobs<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#my-first-jobs" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My first jobs" title="Direct link to My first jobs">​</a></h3>
<p>In November 2006, I landed my first real job ever. I worked in the cafeteria of the <a href="https://provo.mtc.byu.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Provo Missionary Training Centre</a> (MTC). My duties were straightforward: clean the kitchen and serving areas and restock chafing dishes that were running low. Despite the simplicity, I was never trained how I thought I should've been, and I often felt lost in the job. It certainly didn't help that I earned minimum wage and not a cent more.</p>
<p>A few months later, a cousin of mine who worked for <a href="https://www.byutv.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BYU Broadcasting</a> got me an interview for a job as an English-Portuguese translator. His boss offered me 25¢ above minimum wage, and I accepted without hesitation. My cousin became my supervisor and mentor for my four-month stint at that job and we often hung out together after work.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="money-stress">Money stress<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#money-stress" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Money stress" title="Direct link to Money stress">​</a></h3>
<p>I worked all 20 weekly hours that my immigration status allowed me to, but money was still always tight. At some point in the fall of '06, the little cash my mother had left me ran out, and I realized that it was hard to make my money stretch all the way to the next paycheque. I started skipping breakfast and supper and set aside a $8-10 budget for a daily midday meal. Taco Bell and Little Ceasar's gave me the best bank for my buck, and that's what I mostly ate during that first year in university.</p>
<p>On Sundays, I went to my aunt's after church to enjoy my only decent, home-cooked meal all week. I also visited my cousins who lived nearby during the week to scavenge their leftovers. With their permission, of course.</p>
<p>In spite of this frugal regimen, there were a few times when I ran out of money a day or two before payday. When this happened, I powered through the hunger and didn't eat until I had money again. I didn't want to keep begging for food from my cousins. I would've used credit cards if I knew what they were.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#user-content-fn-1-4684dd" id="user-content-fnref-1-4684dd" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></p>
<p>When the cousin who worked with me found out I hadn't eaten in a while during one of these forced fasting sessions, he went to the pizza joint he side-gigged at and brought me a whole Hawaiian pizza, free of charge. Hawaiian has been my favourite kind of pizza ever since.</p>
<p>I haven't talked to this cousin in over a decade. There seems to have been a dispute that caused some family members to sever ties with one another, but I wasn't in Utah when that happened. I don't know what was said, I don't know who was right or wrong, but I'll always remember this estranged cousin for his kindness toward me when I was a young man.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-4684dd">
<p>I did have a Best Buy credit card at the time, but I didn't know how it worked. My cousin helped me get it so I could "build my credit." I didn't know what that meant, and I only used the credit card once. I paid off the balance on the same day of the purchase and never used it again. To this day, I don't know if I could've used the card for non-Best Buy purchases. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#user-content-fnref-1-4684dd" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques</name>
            <email>coelhoigor@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/icasm</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[2. First year in New Jersey]]></title>
        <id>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey</id>
        <link href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey"/>
        <updated>2024-04-26T00:01:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-a-mission">What's a mission?<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#whats-a-mission" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What's a mission?" title="Direct link to What's a mission?">​</a></h2>
<p>During that first year at BYU, I got a call to serve as a full-time missionary for <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints</a> in New Jersey. I was to leave in May 2007.</p>
<p>The Church sends missionaries to places far from their homes and calls them to share the message of the <a href="https://www.comeuntochrist.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">restored Gospel of Jesus Christ</a> with the people who live there. In practice, this means missionaries spend most of their day-to-day finding people willing to listen to them so they can visit them in their homes, share a set of spiritual messages, and bring them to church on Sundays.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="slow-of-speech">"Slow of speech"<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#slow-of-speech" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to &quot;Slow of speech&quot;" title="Direct link to &quot;Slow of speech&quot;">​</a></h3>
<p>Nephi, a prophet in the <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Book of Mormon</a>, wrote that he was not "mighty in writing, like unto speaking."<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#user-content-fn-1-1641e7" id="user-content-fnref-1-1641e7" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> I'm the opposite.</p>
<p>Being a full-time missionary was extremely uncomfortable for me.</p>
<p>Knocking on random doors, stopping people on the street, feeling empathy for strangers, sharing my faith in the hopes that people would feel the way I did about it. None of these things came easy to me. A sense of religious obligation and the camaraderie of my fellow missionaries buoyed me up during those two years of near-constant rejection and derision.</p>
<p>I was not a very good missionary. I was obedient and hard-working, but had little to show for my efforts. I struggled to get people to attend church, and in two years, I only helped one person be baptized into the Church. They left a week later and never returned.</p>
<p>As a missionary, I operated on the assumption that sharing my convictions was enough, but the truth is that effective missionaries leverage charisma and emotional appeal to get people to commit. Just like salespeople. And I'm no salesperson.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nomenclature">Nomenclature<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#nomenclature" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nomenclature" title="Direct link to Nomenclature">​</a></h3>
<p>Missionaries work in companionships (usually pairs, but also trios) and count their time on the mission field in terms of <em>transfers</em>, i.e., periods of six weeks.</p>
<p>Each companionship is assigned to work in an area with fixed limits (we had detailed maps for them). At the end of each transfer, the mission's top leaders decide whether a missionary should stay in the area they are currently serving in or move to a new area. On average, missionaries spend 3-4 transfers in one area, where they cycle through a couple of companions.</p>
<p>I served in seven areas.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="first-areas">First areas<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#first-areas" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to First areas" title="Direct link to First areas">​</a></h2>
<p>Even though I was called to serve in English, my mission leaders placed me in Riverside when I arrived on the field so I could work with the area's large Portuguese-speaking population.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="riverside">Riverside<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#riverside" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Riverside" title="Direct link to Riverside">​</a></h3>
<p>I didn't get along with my first companion. I felt sad and lonely that first transfer, especially at night. We lasted one transfer together. My next companion was on his last transfer. It was summer, he was ready to go home, and we didn't accomplish much of consequence either.</p>
<p>I suffered from sleep paralysis in Riverside. It happened twice. The first time was scary, but I realized what was happening and weathered it. The second time was much worse. I heard noises and saw figures. One of those figures was a pale man with a black beard and bloodshot eyes. He got close to me, face to face, and howled at me.</p>
<p>Some time later, I dreamed with Jesus Christ. He was much taller than me, and he hugged me warmly for a long time. I knew it was just a dream, but it made me feel better, and I haven't had sleep paralysis ever since.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="burlington">Burlington<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#burlington" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Burlington" title="Direct link to Burlington">​</a></h3>
<p>After two transfers in Riverside, I was moved to nearby Burlington and placed in a trio with another Brazilian missionary. We were to keep working with the Portuguese-speaking people of the area. We worked hard and had a lot of fun, but we were not able to get a group of Brazilians to come to church consistently like we had been tasked to do.</p>
<p>In Burlington, I discovered that missionaries have their own folklore. Some of it was harmless fun, like silly traditions and superstitions. For instance, some missionaries I knew kissed their right-hand knuckles and fist-bumped the roofs of their cars whenever they crossed an intersection with a yellow light. They did it either to avoid getting a ticket or to have good luck with the ladies after the mission. Maybe both.</p>
<p>Some other aspects of missionary folklore were more pernicious. My wife has advised me against writing in detail about the sensationalistic, baseless rumours some missionaries and members who had served missions liked to spread. Suffice it to say that one could tell a person's sexual anxieties by the rumours they perpetuated.</p>
<p>I didn't participate in missionary folklore, harmless or otherwise. I thought it was all detrimental to the work we hoped to accomplish.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="switch-to-spanish">Switch to Spanish<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#switch-to-spanish" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Switch to Spanish" title="Direct link to Switch to Spanish">​</a></h2>
<p>When I was in Burlington, my Mission President reached out to me. Our interaction went something like this:</p>
<p>"How's your Spanish, Elder Marques?," he asked me.</p>
<p>"It's OK, I guess. Spanish is similar enough to Portuguese that I can understand like 70%. I don't know how to speak it, though."</p>
<p>"That's probably good enough. I will be transferring you to Freehold, where you will be a senior companion and serve in Spanish. Good luck."</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="freehold">Freehold<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#freehold" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Freehold" title="Direct link to Freehold">​</a></h3>
<p>My first companion in Freehold was eccentric. Maybe he was neurodivergent, or had a personality disorder. During our daily language study in the morning, he chose to study Russian instead of Spanish, even though we never interacted with any Russians. When we visited people, he'd often refuse to speak, close his eyes, and go to sleep while I was speaking. One time he even ate a house centipede just to be funny.</p>
<p>Regardless, the more I learned Spanish and interacted with Latin American immigrants, the more I became enamoured with the language, the people, and their cultures. My Mission President's decision to put me in a Spanish-speaking area had a butterfly effect in my life that I'm very thankful for.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-brunswick">New Brunswick<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#new-brunswick" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New Brunswick" title="Direct link to New Brunswick">​</a></h3>
<p>Congregations in the Church are called "wards" or "branches," depending on their size.</p>
<p>In Freehold, Spanish-speaking members of the Church were few and had to attend the English-language ward. Visitors felt alienated by the language barrier, and were not motivated to return. In New Brunswick, my next area, there <em>was</em> a Spanish-speaking branch. This gave us the support we needed to do our best work.</p>
<p>Even though it was not as bad as Trenton or Camden, New Brunswick had some sketchy neighbourhoods. As missionaries, we did most of our work in these poorer neighbourhoods because many people who lived there appreciated the hope and stability our messages brought them. The rate of rejection was lower.</p>
<p>We biked everywhere with our paper maps and got to know the city very well, warts and all. I loved New Brunswick and felt at home there for the first time in my mission.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="training">Training<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#training" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Training" title="Direct link to Training">​</a></h4>
<p>After a transfer in New Brunswick, my mission leaders assigned me to train a "greenie," i.e., to be the first companion of a brand-new missionary.</p>
<p>Training is a big milestone for missionaries, and I took the task seriously. I got lucky and the new missionary, who was from Mexico but had been living in the US since the age of 5, was a great man. He helped me become fluent in Spanish, and we became fast friends.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="river-of-blood">River of blood<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#river-of-blood" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to River of blood" title="Direct link to River of blood">​</a></h4>
<p>My companion and I shared an apartment across Boyd Park on Route 18 with an English-speaking companionship. There was a friendly member of the English ward who lived a block away from us, so our flatmates visited him frequently. This member was notoriously generous, and gave the English missionaries a lot of food and clothing.</p>
<p>One evening, this member gave our flatmates kilograms upon kilograms of venison. He was not a hunter and we had no idea how he had gotten the venison, but the English missionaries didn't want to look a gift horse in the mouth and brought the meat back to our apartment. We fit what little we could in the freezer and left the rest sitting on the kitchen counter, then we went to bed.</p>
<p>We were unsupervised 19- and 20-year-olds and did not see a single problem in our plan.</p>
<p>The next morning, I woke up to one of the English missionaries yelling, "What in the world?! Guys, wake up! Come here! There's a river of blood!" He'd gone to the kitchen half-asleep in the morning and saw that the meat sitting on the counter had thawed and that <strong>A LOT</strong> of myoglobin had seeped through the packaging and pooled on the floor.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hospital-visit">Hospital visit<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#hospital-visit" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hospital visit" title="Direct link to Hospital visit">​</a></h4>
<p>Most people resented us when we knocked their doors unannounced or stopped them on the street. We only did it because we felt it was important; nobody likes inconveniencing others and being rejected dozens of times a day.</p>
<p>Consequently, we were constantly looking for better ways to find receptive people. One day, we decided to start calling members of our branch who hadn't been to church in a long time. Maybe they were ready to start attending church again and had family members or friends who'd be interested in having us over.</p>
<p>We found out that a lady from our branch was in hospital, awaiting an important surgery. "Is it OK if we pay you a visit to give you a blessing?," we asked her over the phone. She agreed, and we visited her that same day. Her boyfriend did not like us very much, but he warmed up to us as we continue to visit their family after she was discharged.</p>
<p>The last I heard was that, shortly after I left New Brunswick, they got married, he got baptized, and they were a happy family.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="v-days">V-days<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#v-days" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to V-days" title="Direct link to V-days">​</a></h4>
<p>Back then, missionaries could only communicate with people outside of their areas by snail mail (with very few exceptions). In New Brunswick, I received an unexpected letter from a childhood friend, who had moved away from Curitiba nearly a decade before.</p>
<p>Her name was Verónica, but everyone called her Vero. Vero's letters were tender and entertaining, and I did my best to reply in kind.</p>
<p>When she sent me her picture, I was struck. She was drop-dead gorgeous.</p>
<p>I was developing feelings for her, but we were told to "lock our hearts" as missionaries so we could focus on the work. That was hard to do, what with our teenage hormones going off.</p>
<p>So I made a decision. I would only read and reply to Vero's letters on Wednesdays, which was our mission's day off. Wednesdays were called <em>preparation days</em>, or "P-days" for short, but everybody knew that they were my special <strong>V-days</strong>.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-1641e7">
<p><a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/33?lang=eng&amp;id=p1#p1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2 Nephi 33:1</a>. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/first-year-in-new-jersey#user-content-fnref-1-1641e7" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques</name>
            <email>coelhoigor@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/icasm</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[3. Second year in New Jersey]]></title>
        <id>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey</id>
        <link href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey"/>
        <updated>2024-04-26T00:02:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="long-branch">Long Branch<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#long-branch" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Long Branch" title="Direct link to Long Branch">​</a></h2>
<p>A year into my mission, I was transferred to Long Branch on the Jersey shore.</p>
<p>That area showed me the extent of wealth inequality in the US. We'd meet undocumented men who worked as day labourers and lived in cramped rooms with no beds or furniture of any kind. We'd meet children with rotten teeth and tattered clothing practically raising themselves on the street because it was better than being home with their parents.</p>
<p>Then we'd drive down Ocean Ave and gawk at the mansions in Deal.</p>
<p>One time, my companion and I were caught in an unexpected thunderstorm while we were out on the street. We stopped under an eave to wait out the storm. A few moments later, this happened:</p>
<ol>
<li>A minivan parked on the street.</li>
<li>A man got off the minivan.</li>
<li>He hurried to a house nearby and entered it.</li>
<li>He came out of the house with an umbrella.</li>
<li>He handed us the umbrella.</li>
<li>He got back in the minivan and drove off.</li>
</ol>
<p>That was one of the most random things that has ever happened to me.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="atlantic-city">Atlantic City<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#atlantic-city" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Atlantic City" title="Direct link to Atlantic City">​</a></h2>
<p>I spent my second winter in the mission in Atlantic City. Come Christmastime, we said yes to everyone who invited us for supper on Christmas eve. We went from home to home to home on a sort of holiday binge and ate a ridiculous amount of food that December 24<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ac-branch">AC branch<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#ac-branch" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AC branch" title="Direct link to AC branch">​</a></h3>
<p>We didn't have an actual church building in AC. Spanish-speaking members in the area attended a branch that rented a space in the city. This branch held two sacrament meetings each Sunday, one in the morning and one in the evening. No other congregation in the Church does this, as far as I'm aware. Ostensibly, they did this to accommodate the members' schedules, who had competing work shifts at the AC casinos.</p>
<p>It didn't really work out, though. Most people came in the morning. The attendance for the evening services was abysmal, and the few people who came consistently in the evening just took turns giving talks and saying the prayers. It was a little sad.</p>
<p>The AC Spanish branch no longer exists. It was moribund when I was there during the 2008 recession, and must have gotten worse when several casinos closed down in the mid 2010s. I imagine this downturn drove off the Spanish-speaking immigrants in the area, whom the casinos employed as cooks, housekeepers, busboys, etc. The pandemic and the rise of sports betting and online gambling in recent years must have sealed the deal.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="confrontation">Confrontation<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#confrontation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Confrontation" title="Direct link to Confrontation">​</a></h3>
<p>We were used to belligerent people. We were not shy about defending our beliefs when someone was hostile to us, but we tried to avoid confrontation as much as possible because it was not productive. It was a tug of war with no winners.</p>
<p>We lived by this verse in The Book of Mormon,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>He that hath the spirit of contention is not of [God], but is of the devil, who is the father of contention, and he stirreth up the hearts of men to contend with anger, one with another.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#user-content-fn-1-4707f3" id="user-content-fnref-1-4707f3" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When we sensed that people just wanted to argue with us, we tried to retreat diplomatically. If they weren't going to share our beliefs, at least we hoped they'd remember us as decent people. But some people trapped us before attacking us (verbally, mostly).</p>
<p>Whenever my companion and I were tired of working in AC, we took the train to Egg Harbor City and worked there. One of those days, a man answered a door that we knocked and talked to us. That was rare.</p>
<p>"Elder... Mar-KAY? Mar-KEE? What is that, French?," he asked me.</p>
<p>"Portuguese. You can call me Mar-KES. I'm Brazilian."</p>
<p>"Brazilian? You're white. Blue eyes. Where're your folks from?"</p>
<p>I got that all the time. People did not realize Brazil is a diverse country. But this man was not ignorant. I could tell he was baiting me.</p>
<p>"They're also Brazilian," I replied. "In fact, my ancestors have been in Brazil since the 1700s. And before that, Portugal. Pretty standard for Brazilians."</p>
<p>"Not at all. You're pure white. Not a hint of black or brown. You come from a lineage of untainted slave owners and Indian killers, don't you? Hundreds of years in Brazil and not one of your ancestors wanted to sleep with a black lady?"<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#user-content-fn-2-4707f3" id="user-content-fnref-2-4707f3" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup></p>
<p>I didn't know how to respond. The man was right, at least partially. I do have slave-owning ancestors. But that's just one branch of my family tree. I also have a freedwoman ancestor from the early 1800s in Minas Gerais. My maternal grandmother's maternal grandmother came from an indigenous group in southern Maranhão.</p>
<p>But there was no point in contradicting the man. He bid us go in, and we sat in his living room. We never refused an invitation to enter a home. He continued to be edgy and toy with us just to see how we would react. He was bored on a Saturday afternoon, and we were his entertainment.</p>
<p>"I used to be gay, you know. I know how you guys feel about gays," he said. The Church had been on the news recently for sponsoring ads in support of <a href="https://library.law.howard.edu/civilrightshistory/lgbtq/prop8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Proposition 8</a>, which banned same-sex marriage in California that year. "But I grew out of that," he continued. "As soon as I tried ladies, I realized I really, really liked them." He the described how he had met his wife, who was upstairs, in graphic detail.</p>
<p>I didn't feel threatened by that man, but I did feel icky after the visit. Thankfully, later that day we found a nice Honduran family and made baleadas with them. They were modest and kind and sharing a meal with them restored my spirit.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="princeton">Princeton<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#princeton" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Princeton" title="Direct link to Princeton">​</a></h2>
<p>My mission leaders sent me to Princeton, an English-speaking area, to finish my mission. Spring in Princeton was unreal. The streets were fragrant, abuzz with bumblebees, and dressed in vibrant colours.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="companionship-problems">Companionship problems<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#companionship-problems" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Companionship problems" title="Direct link to Companionship problems">​</a></h3>
<p>My time in Princeton was weird. On the one hand, I was at my boldest as a missionary. The apathy of the university community toward us somehow energized me, and I started to feel empowered by rejection. I walked upright and did not have a problem talking to anyone.</p>
<p>On the other hand, I hardly connected with anybody. My first companion there was terrible. He refused to talk to people and chewed me out openly in front of anyone. He'd been seeing a therapist, but the pressures of missionary work got to him and he ended up going home a few weeks later, six months before his release date.</p>
<p>The missionary that replaced him was was lazy and petty, but not as mean. We worked less than we should have and had zero success. With one exception.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="technically-i-taught-at-princeton">Technically, I taught at Princeton<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#technically-i-taught-at-princeton" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Technically, I taught at Princeton" title="Direct link to Technically, I taught at Princeton">​</a></h3>
<p>A woman in her 20s was receptive to our messages. She was was pursuing a graduate degree at Princeton and had become good friends with a classmate who was a member of our ward. I'm not sure if she had ulterior motives vis-à-vis her friend, but I don't think she did. She was bright and genuine. My companion and I shared our messages with her and her friend once a week in a classroom on campus. She eventually lost interest, and I still blame myself for that.</p>
<p>Missionaries say they are "trunky" when they feel indolent toward the end of their missions, i.e., their trunks are packed and they are fixated about going home. Regrets aside, I was never "trunky" in Princeton and continued to work hard until my last day on the field in late May 2009.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-4707f3">
<p><a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/11?lang=eng&amp;id=p29#p29" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">3 Nephi 11:29</a> <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#user-content-fnref-1-4707f3" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-2-4707f3">
<p>The way he spoke was ... much more <strong>colourful</strong> than how I feel comfortable writing. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/second-year-in-new-jersey#user-content-fnref-2-4707f3" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques</name>
            <email>coelhoigor@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/icasm</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[4. Long-distance relationship]]></title>
        <id>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship</id>
        <link href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship"/>
        <updated>2024-04-26T00:03:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is an account of my adult life in essay form. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="in-person-v-days">In-person V-days<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#in-person-v-days" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to In-person V-days" title="Direct link to In-person V-days">​</a></h2>
<p>After I was honourably released from my mission, I met with <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/church/leader/richard-g-scott?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Elder Richard Scott</a>, a member of the Church's <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/learn/quorum-of-the-twelve-apostles?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quorum of Twelve Apostles</a>. Among other things, he told me that my next priority should be finding an "eternal companion." My mind went to Vero.</p>
<p>I finished my mission in May 2009, four months before I had to resume my studies at BYU, and I chose to spend that time in Curitiba. Vero had broken up with her previous boyfriend some time before and agreed to come to Brazil to see if we were a good match.</p>
<p>We were. We clicked instantly. She smelled good and I liked the way she spoke Spanish. We had fun getting to know each other and going to Curitiba's tourist destinations. I even serenaded her with a song I'd written on the piano. When we were in line at a fast food joint, I hugged her from behind, she turned her face around, and we kissed for the first time. I still get butterflies in my stomach thinking about that moment.</p>
<p>When I felt shy about telling her something, I spelled out the words on the palms of her hand with my index finger, Helen Keller-style. After she'd been in Brazil for a few days, we found ourselves in the back of my parents' car on a long road trip. I asked her, "Will you be my girlfriend?," with my tactile writing system. She said no; she wanted me to "propose" out loud and in a more appropriate setting.</p>
<p>A few days later, I asked her again, out loud in a better place, and she said yes. We agreed to have a long-distance relationship while we were in university, and I promised to do my best to visit her in Chile at least once a year on my summer breaks.</p>
<p>My parents loved Vero. After she went back home, my father told me he'd support our relationship and covered the cost of an airfare to Chile so I could see her again before going to Provo. I met Vero's family and friends, and fell more in love with her.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="classical-89">Classical 89<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#classical-89" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Classical 89" title="Direct link to Classical 89">​</a></h2>
<p>When I finally returned to Provo, I landed a job interview at the university's classical music radio station, <a href="https://www.classical89.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Classical 89 (KBYU-FM)</a>. It was the perfect fit for me, a music major and classical music nerd.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="interview">Interview<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#interview" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Interview" title="Direct link to Interview">​</a></h3>
<p>The interview was a bit more intense than I expected. At one point, one of the interviewers asked me if I was able to tell the conductor and orchestra of a recording just by listening. No way. Not even nowadays. He said he could. It was not a weird power move; he was a nice guy and hoped to bond with me by nerding out together.</p>
<p>The interviewers wanted to make sure that:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was passionate about classical music.</li>
<li>I could write "my way out of a paper bag."</li>
<li>I had a good voice for radio.</li>
</ul>
<p>I checked two out of these three boxes; my accent and lack of experience got in the way of the third. Nevertheless, I got the job.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="job-duties">Job duties<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#job-duties" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Job duties" title="Direct link to Job duties">​</a></h3>
<p>They gave me the title of <em>assistant producer</em> and told me that that was not the position that I had applied for—that had gone to another young man—but that they had liked me and wanted to keep me because another student was going to graduate soon anyway.</p>
<p>I worked happily at Classical 89 until I graduated in 2013.</p>
<p>My main tasks were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Assist with the logistics of concert recordings</li>
<li>Edit and package interviews and live performances for the air</li>
<li>Support the full-time announcers in their shifts</li>
<li>Record my own shifts on weekday evenings and weekends</li>
</ul>
<p>I've always chosen my words carefully because I hated being misunderstood as a child. Being an assistant producer at Classical 89 helped me elevate that personality trait into communicative power. I learned a lot by reading aloud what I'd written and then revising it until it sounded good enough to say it on the air.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="crisis-of-self-awareness">Crisis of self-awareness<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#crisis-of-self-awareness" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Crisis of self-awareness" title="Direct link to Crisis of self-awareness">​</a></h3>
<p>One day, I checked out a portable Zoom recorder. Strangely, I noticed that the recorder's storage was almost full, even though everyone tended to format the recorders before checking them in. I listened to the recording to find out who'd left it there so I could ask for their permission to clear the memory and use the recorder for my project.</p>
<p>It was the young man who had gotten the position I had applied for. I'd been working with him for several months and I thought he was a nice guy. In the recording, he was interviewing his wife, as a joke.</p>
<p>Then, out of nowhere, he began to role-play as me.</p>
<p>He put on a thick accent and started acting stupid. In his role-play, he, or rather, <em>I</em> was courting his wife like a lustful jackass while she refused my advances, laughing. I thought it was weird that she acted like she knew who I was, even though we'd never met. Was I the person that couple liked gossiping about? Were there other people who thought I was like that?</p>
<p>I didn't hear the whole thing. I couldn't, I was too perplexed. Maybe that parody of me was a truer version of myself than the person I thought I was. But I was not offended. I've always enjoyed making people laugh, regardless of the reason.</p>
<p>I pondered on the rare and fleeting nature of self-awareness. In the years since, I have accepted self-awareness as one my life's most elusive goals, and made peace with the fact that I may never know who I really am,<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#user-content-fn-1-155e34" id="user-content-fnref-1-155e34" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> or who I appear to be to other people.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I wish I had saved that recording.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="chile-2010">Chile 2010<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#chile-2010" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Chile 2010" title="Direct link to Chile 2010">​</a></h2>
<p>Vero had a friend from Chiguayante, her hometown, who had moved to Provo recently. I'd met her in Chile and thought she was great fun, so we got together once or twice that year. On 27 February 2010, she called me in the morning.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="27f">27F<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#27f" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 27F" title="Direct link to 27F">​</a></h3>
<p>"Have you had any news from Vero?" Her voice wavered with a hint of desperation. "I can't get in touch with my family!"</p>
<p>"Why? What's wrong?"</p>
<p>"You haven't heard?"</p>
<p>"Heard what?"</p>
<p>"There's been a massive earthquake near Conce, one of the worst ones ever! And a tsunami, too. Phone, internet, nothing's working, so nobody knows if people there are OK." (She was right; that earthquake, nicknamed 27F, remains the eighth most intense seismic activity in recorded history.)</p>
<p>We commiserated with each other and tried calling, emailing, using social media, anything to reach the people we loved down there. Eventually, she was able to talk to her family, and I got a call from Vero, who apparently had borrowed a satellite phone.</p>
<p>Vero told me that the earthquake had been vicious, her family was OK, and their home appeared to have suffered no structural damage. Life was complicated with severe aftershocks, looting, damaged roads, and a lack of services, but they were safe albeit traumatized and constantly on edge. She told not to worry, that her family, neighbourhood, and Church ward were managing, then she hung up.</p>
<p>Vero has fascinating stories about that time, but they are hers to tell. On my end, all I could do was wait and hope for the best.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="world-cup">World Cup<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#world-cup" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to World Cup" title="Direct link to World Cup">​</a></h3>
<p>Chileans are proud of their resilience and the country soon resumed activities, even though many people continued to struggle for years with the after-effects of 27F.</p>
<p>When I visited Chile that summer (which was winter in the Southern Hemisphere), I was most impressed by the ruins of the <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edificio_Alto_R%C3%ADo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alto Río</a>, a 15-storey building near the Biobío river that broke in half and collapsed during the earthquake. An <a href="https://www.architectural-review.com/buildings/atanacio-soza-arquitectos-memorial-27f-a-potential-symbol-of-drastic-change" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">imposing but controversial memorial</a> was erected near the site of the Alto Río in 2013. I also noticed that 27F had become a scapegoat for problems that clearly antedated it, so I started joking with Vero and blaming 27F for any inconvenience I encountered there.</p>
<p>2010 was a World Cup year as well, and Chileans were excited about the prospects of their national team. The Chilean squad did very well in the tournament until they had to go against Brazil in the round of 16, at which point they were properly thrashed, 3-0. That could've caused some friction with my girlfriend, but she was as Brazilian as she was Chilean, and felt comfortable with whatever outcome of that match.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="year-3-at-byu">Year 3 at BYU<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#year-3-at-byu" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Year 3 at BYU" title="Direct link to Year 3 at BYU">​</a></h2>
<p>Fall 2010 marked the beginning of my third year in university. Academically, I was doing very well and qualified for a full-tuition bursary.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alma">ALMA<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#alma" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ALMA" title="Direct link to ALMA">​</a></h3>
<p>Whenever I was not in class or at work, I spent most of my time in the <a href="https://music.byu.edu/facilities/electronic-facilities" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Advanced Lab for Music Applications</a> (ALMA) in BYU's Harris Fine Arts Centre (HFAC). The ALMA had row after row of MIDI keyboards, each with a pair of headphones and a computer with all the music and audio apps I could want. The ALMA was located in a weird annex of the HFAC, away from most foot traffic, so it became a sort of sanctuary for me.</p>
<p>I thought back to my reticence about applying to BYU, and the ALMA made me feel grateful for my parents' insistence.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="move-to-orem">Move to Orem<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#move-to-orem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Move to Orem" title="Direct link to Move to Orem">​</a></h3>
<p>In late 2010, my parents decided to spend a small fortune they had been saving to buy a condo in Orem near exit 273 of the I-15. It had high ceilings, three bedrooms, two bathrooms, and a nice balcony. It was a couple of blocks away from Winco, my favourite grocery store ever. I loved that condo and never took it for granted.</p>
<p>As 2010 came to a close, I was happy and stable. Now I just needed to bring Vero to the US and start a family with her.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-155e34">
<p>My fellow members of the Church might cringe when they read this since we're all taught that being children of God should be the basis of our identity. This much I know. It's all other parts of who I am that bewilder me. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#user-content-fnref-1-155e34" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques</name>
            <email>coelhoigor@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/icasm</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>