<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques Blog</title>
        <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story</link>
        <description>Igor Coelho A. S. Marques Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[1. From Curitiba to Provo]]></title>
            <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo</link>
            <guid>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="college-or-university-both">College or university? Both!<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#college-or-university-both" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to College or university? Both!" title="Direct link to College or university? Both!">​</a></h2>
<p>In late 2005, at the age of 17, I took the entrance exams for <a href="https://sacod.ufpr.br/artes/musica-licenciatura-e-bacharelado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">music production at the Federal University of Paraná</a> (UFPR) and for <a href="https://embap.curitiba1.unespar.edu.br/menu-ensino/graduacao/bacharelado-em-composicao-e-regencia" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">music composition and conducting at the state's College of Music and Fine Arts</a> (Belas). I really only cared about the program at Belas, whose conservatory I'd already been attending since I was 10, but my parents and my school teachers expected me to apply to UFPR because it was the most prestigious university in the city.</p>
<p>I passed the exams with flying colours and enrolled in both programs simultaneously.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ufpr">UFPR<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#ufpr" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to UFPR" title="Direct link to UFPR">​</a></h3>
<p>During the day, I attended UFPR. I felt impressed by my professors' credentials, most of whom had earned their terminal degrees and made a name for themselves in the US and Europe. Still, lectures were three-hour-long information dumps and the practical labs were a little too crowded to be useful. I enjoyed parts of it, such as socializing with like-minded people, but exams were hard and I struggled academically.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="belas">Belas<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#belas" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Belas" title="Direct link to Belas">​</a></h3>
<p>When my day at UFPR ended, I bussed downtown to Belas, where college courses were held in the evening. I remember some things about those classes vividly.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="video-game-music">Video game music<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#video-game-music" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Video game music" title="Direct link to Video game music">​</a></h4>
<p>One instructor asked us about our long-term goals. "I want to write music for video games," I replied. Everyone chuckled, thinking I was joking.</p>
<p>"Oh, you're serious...," the instructor realized.</p>
<p>I was. I knew it was a viable career choice, even then. I wasn't offended by their laughing, though; my answer was unusual for the time and place and laughing was a fair reaction. Besides, I've always enjoyed making people laugh, regardless of the reason.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="counterpoint">Counterpoint<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#counterpoint" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Counterpoint" title="Direct link to Counterpoint">​</a></h4>
<p>Another instructor, who taught counterpoint, had us listen to and analyze Victoria's <a href="https://youtu.be/9xPh-fXYAc4?si=BvWIHRapQ_IhjSPp" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>O magnum mysterium</em></a>.</p>
<p>I had <strong>never</strong> heard anything like that. It moved me to tears.</p>
<p>I would have similar experiences later in life with the final movement of Mozart's <a href="https://youtu.be/UsNk-7j9lpY?si=Urm8cFJn8IGiyObl&amp;t=1588" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"Jupiter" Symphony</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/dkfVzCZ68_Q?si=WMq4gcyNpIRFHNVd" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Mille regretz</em></a> by Josquin des Prez, and some of Monteverdi's <a href="https://youtu.be/YUgIJ212IVg?si=A0skWk9NgEqHSxVX" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">madrigals</a>. Come to think of it, beautiful music has made me cry much more as an adult than sadness.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nightly-commutes">Nightly commutes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#nightly-commutes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nightly commutes" title="Direct link to Nightly commutes">​</a></h4>
<p>After classes ended at about 22:30, I bussed back home with my best friend from church, who was a first-year student at Belas like me. Despite the late hour, buses were bustling with people who also had night classes in nearby colleges. It was a vibrant atmosphere, and my friend and I had some of the most fun conversations I've ever had on those commutes.</p>
<p>I felt fortunate to have a friend like him, with whom I could connect deeply on many levels. Our paths would diverge in later years, and I was never to regain a friendship like that in my adult life.</p>
<p>My home was seven blocks away from the bus stop. I was often accosted by aggressive stray dogs on the way that late at night. I think they felt territorial because the streets were deserted and they were after females in heat. I soon learned that they'd leave me alone if I threw rocks at them, so I always picked up some as soon as I got off the bus. I had to run a few times, but I was never bitten.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="provo-bound">Provo-bound<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#provo-bound" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Provo-bound" title="Direct link to Provo-bound">​</a></h2>
<p>Studying in two different institutions was unsustainable. Thankfully, it didn't last long.</p>
<p>Many of my older cousins were attending <a href="https://www.byu.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brigham Young University</a> (BYU) at the time, and my parents thought I should too. At first, I resisted the idea, but they convinced me that going abroad would give me the best chance to succeed as a musician, and I acceded.</p>
<p>While I was a student of UFPR and Belas, I also had to scramble to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Prepare for and take an English proficiency test.</li>
<li>Record myself playing some piano pieces for my portfolio.</li>
<li>Schedule the ecclesiastical interviews BYU required.</li>
<li>Fill the application form and write essays about my background and merits.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn't know that the school year in the Northern Hemisphere was different than ours in Brazil, so I completed my application months after the deadline had passed. I applied so late that BYU had already sent out decision notifications by the time they received my application package.</p>
<p>Yet, somehow, I was admitted to start in the fall of that same year. My father maintains that this was only possible due to the intercession of an old family friend who knew someone in the admissions office. I think my father overestimates the pull this family friend had, but whatever the case, I got in.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="naïveté">Naïveté<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#na%C3%AFvet%C3%A9" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Naïveté" title="Direct link to Naïveté">​</a></h3>
<p>In August 2006, I quit my studies in Curitiba and went to Provo with my mother. With the help of my cousins, I rented a shared room a few blocks away from campus. My mother helped me furnish whatever little space I had, and some days later she went back home.</p>
<p>That first year at BYU was very confusing. I understood little about what was happening.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>I didn't know that I had to register for courses and that I had to coordinate them so they wouldn't overlap with each other or with my work schedule. I also didn't know I had to plan how my courses would fulfill university-wide and program-specific requirements. Brazilian universities assigned all students the same course schedule.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I didn't know that applying to the university major I wanted—music theory and composition—was a separate process from applying to the university itself. That was an unwelcome surprise.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I didn't know any of the higher-ed lingo, e.g., undergraduate vs. graduate, and I didn't understand how these words related to my reality. I also didn't know the difference between teaching assistants (TAs), adjunct faculty, and full-time professors, and addressed everyone by the title of "Dr."</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>All I knew was that my family expected me to get good marks, qualify for merit-based bursaries, find a part-time job, and leave on a mission for <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints</a> the following year. That was the path my older cousins had blazed for me.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-first-jobs">My first jobs<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#my-first-jobs" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My first jobs" title="Direct link to My first jobs">​</a></h3>
<p>In November 2006, I landed my first real job ever. I worked in the cafeteria of the <a href="https://provo.mtc.byu.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Provo Missionary Training Center</a> (MTC). My duties were straightforward: clean the kitchen and serving areas and restock chafing dishes that were running low. Despite the simplicity, I was never trained how I thought I should've been, and I often felt lost in the job. It certainly didn't help that I earned minimum wage and not a cent more.</p>
<p>A few months later, a cousin of mine who worked for <a href="https://www.byutv.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BYU Broadcasting</a> got me an interview for a job as an English-Portuguese translator. His boss offered me 25¢ above minimum wage, and I accepted without hesitation. My cousin became my supervisor and mentor for my four-month stint at that job and we often hung out together after work.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="money-stress">Money stress<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#money-stress" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Money stress" title="Direct link to Money stress">​</a></h3>
<p>My student visa allowed me to work 20 weekly hours, and I worked all 20 hours every week, but money was still always tight. At some point in the fall of '06, the little cash my mother had left me ran out, and I realized that it was hard to make my money stretch all the way to the next paycheque. I started skipping breakfast and supper and set aside a $8-10 budget for a daily midday meal. Taco Bell and Little Ceasar's gave me the best bank for my buck, and that's what I mostly ate during that first year in university.</p>
<p>On Sundays, I went to my aunt's after church to enjoy my only decent, home-cooked meal all week. I also visited my cousins who lived nearby during the week to scavenge their leftovers. With their permission, of course.</p>
<p>In spite of this frugal regimen, there were a few times when I ran out of money a day or two before payday. When this happened, I powered through the hunger and didn't eat until I had money again. I didn't want to keep begging for food from my cousins. I would've used credit cards if I knew what they were.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#user-content-fn-1-4684dd" id="user-content-fnref-1-4684dd" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></p>
<p>When the cousin who worked with me found out I hadn't eaten in a while during one of these forced fasting sessions, he went to the pizza joint he side-gigged at and brought me a whole Hawaiian pizza, free of charge. Hawaiian has been my favourite kind of pizza ever since.</p>
<p>I haven't talked to this cousin in over a decade. There seems to have been a dispute that caused some family members to sever ties with one another, but I wasn't in Utah when that happened. I don't know what was said, I don't know who was right or wrong, but I'll always remember this estranged cousin for his kindness toward me when I was a young man.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-4684dd">
<p>I did have a Best Buy credit card at the time, but I didn't know how it worked. My cousin helped me get it so I could "build my credit." I didn't know what that meant, and I only used the credit card once. I paid off the balance on the same day of the purchase and never used it again. To this day, I don't know if I could've used the card for non-Best Buy purchases. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#user-content-fnref-1-4684dd" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>coelhoigor@gmail.com (Igor Coelho A. S. Marques)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2. Mission (Year 1)]]></title>
            <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one</link>
            <guid>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-a-mission">What's a mission?<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#whats-a-mission" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What's a mission?" title="Direct link to What's a mission?">​</a></h2>
<p>During that first year at BYU, I got a call to serve as a full-time missionary for <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints</a> in New Jersey. I was to leave in May 2007.</p>
<p>The Church sends missionaries to places far from their homes and calls them to share the message of the <a href="https://www.comeuntochrist.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">restored Gospel of Jesus Christ</a> with the people who live there. In practice, this means missionaries spend most of their day-to-day finding people willing to listen to them so they can visit them in their homes, share a set of spiritual messages, and bring them to church on Sundays.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="introversion">Introversion<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#introversion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introversion" title="Direct link to Introversion">​</a></h3>
<p>Nephi, a prophet in the <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Book of Mormon</a>, wrote that he was not "mighty in writing, like unto speaking."<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#user-content-fn-1-61b28f" id="user-content-fnref-1-61b28f" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> I'm the exact opposite.</p>
<p>Being a full-time missionary was extremely uncomfortable for me.</p>
<p>Knocking on random doors, stopping people on the street, feeling empathy for strangers, sharing my faith in the hopes that people would feel the way I did about it. None of these things came easy to me. A sense of religious obligation and the camaraderie of my fellow missionaries buoyed me up during those two years of near-constant rejection and derision.</p>
<p>I was not a very good missionary. I was obedient and hard-working, but had little to show for my efforts. I struggled to get people to attend church, and in two years, I only helped one person be baptized into the Church. They left a week later and never returned.</p>
<p>As a missionary, I operated on the assumption that sharing my convictions was enough, but the truth is that effective missionaries leverage charisma and emotional appeal to get people to commit. Just like salespeople. And I'm no salesperson.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nomenclature">Nomenclature<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#nomenclature" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nomenclature" title="Direct link to Nomenclature">​</a></h3>
<p>Missionaries work in companionships (usually pairs, but also trios) and count their time on the mission field in terms of <em>transfers</em>, i.e., periods of six weeks.</p>
<p>Each companionship is assigned to work in an area with fixed limits (we had detailed maps for them). At the end of each transfer, the mission's top leaders decide whether a missionary should stay in the area they are currently serving in or move to a new area. On average, missionaries spend 3-4 transfers in one area, where they cycle through a couple of companions.</p>
<p>I served in seven areas.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="first-areas">First areas<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#first-areas" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to First areas" title="Direct link to First areas">​</a></h2>
<p>Even though I was called to serve in English, my mission leaders placed me in Riverside, NJ when I arrived on the field so I could work with the area's large Portuguese-speaking population.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="riverside">Riverside<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#riverside" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Riverside" title="Direct link to Riverside">​</a></h3>
<p>I didn't get along with my first companion. I felt sad and lonely that first transfer, especially at night. We lasted one transfer together. My next companion was on his last transfer. It was summer, he was ready to go home, and we didn't accomplish much of consequence either.</p>
<p>I suffered from sleep paralysis in Riverside. It happened twice. The first time was scary, but I realized what was happening and weathered it. The second time was much worse. I heard noises and saw figures. One of those figures was a pale man with a black beard and bloodshot eyes. He got close to me, face to face, and howled at me.</p>
<p>Some time later, I dreamed with Jesus Christ. He was much taller than me, and he hugged me warmly for a long time. I knew it was just a dream, but it made me feel better, and I haven't had sleep paralysis ever since.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="burlington">Burlington<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#burlington" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Burlington" title="Direct link to Burlington">​</a></h3>
<p>After two transfers in Riverside, I was moved to nearby Burlington, NJ and placed in a trio with another Brazilian missionary. We were to keep working with the Portuguese-speaking people of the area. We worked hard and had a lot of fun, but we were not able to get a group of Brazilians to come to church consistently like we had been tasked to do.</p>
<p>In Burlington, I discovered that missionaries have their own folklore. Some of it was harmless fun, like silly traditions and superstitions. For instance, some missionaries I knew kissed their right-hand knuckles and fist-bumped the roofs of their cars whenever they crossed an intersection with a yellow light. They did it either to avoid getting a ticket or to have good luck with the ladies after the mission. Maybe both.</p>
<p>Some other aspects of missionary folklore were more pernicious. My wife has advised me against writing in detail about the sensationalistic, baseless rumours some missionaries and members who had served missions liked to spread. Suffice it to say that one could tell a person's sexual anxieties by the rumours they perpetuated.</p>
<p>I didn't participate in missionary folklore, harmless or otherwise. I thought it was all detrimental to the work we hoped to accomplish.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="switch-to-spanish">Switch to Spanish<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#switch-to-spanish" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Switch to Spanish" title="Direct link to Switch to Spanish">​</a></h2>
<p>When I was in Burlington, my Mission President reached out to me. Our interaction went something like this:</p>
<p>"How's your Spanish, Elder Marques?," he asked me.</p>
<p>"It's OK, I guess. Spanish is similar enough to Portuguese that I can understand like 70%. I don't know how to speak it, though."</p>
<p>"That's probably good enough. I will be transferring you to Freehold, where you will be a senior companion and serve in Spanish. Good luck."</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="freehold">Freehold<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#freehold" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Freehold" title="Direct link to Freehold">​</a></h3>
<p>My first companion in Freehold, NJ was eccentric. Maybe he was neurodivergent, maybe he had a personality disorder—maybe he was just odd. During our daily language study in the morning, he chose to study Russian instead of Spanish, even though we never interacted with any Russians. When we visited people, he'd often refuse to speak, close his eyes, and go to sleep while I was speaking. One time he even ate a living house centipede just to be funny.</p>
<p>Regardless, the more I learned Spanish and interacted with Latin American immigrants, the more I became enamoured with the language, the people, and their cultures. My Mission President's decision to put me in a Spanish-speaking area had a butterfly effect in my life that I'm very thankful for.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-brunswick">New Brunswick<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#new-brunswick" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New Brunswick" title="Direct link to New Brunswick">​</a></h3>
<p>Congregations in the Church are called "wards" or "branches," depending on their size.</p>
<p>In Freehold, Spanish-speaking members of the Church were few and had to attend the English-language ward. Visitors felt alienated by the language barrier, and were not motivated to return. In New Brunswick, my next area, there <em>was</em> a Spanish-speaking branch. This gave us the support we needed to do our best work.</p>
<p>Even though it was not as bad as Trenton or Camden, New Brunswick had some sketchy neighbourhoods. As missionaries, we did most of our work in these poorer neighbourhoods because many people who lived there appreciated the hope and stability our messages brought them. The rate of rejection was lower.</p>
<p>We biked everywhere with our paper maps and got to know the city very well, warts and all. I loved New Brunswick and felt at home there for the first time in my mission.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="training">Training<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#training" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Training" title="Direct link to Training">​</a></h4>
<p>After a transfer in New Brunswick, my mission leaders assigned me to train a "greenie," i.e., to be the first companion of a brand-new missionary.</p>
<p>Training is a big milestone for missionaries, and I took the task seriously. I got lucky and the new missionary, who was from Mexico but had been living in the US since the age of 5, was a great man. He helped me become fluent in Spanish, and we became fast friends.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="river-of-blood">River of blood<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#river-of-blood" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to River of blood" title="Direct link to River of blood">​</a></h4>
<p>My companion and I shared an apartment across Boyd Park on Route 18 with an English-speaking companionship. There was a friendly member of the English ward who lived a block away from us, so our flatmates visited him frequently. This member was notoriously generous, and gave the English missionaries a lot of food and clothing.</p>
<p>One evening, this member gave our flatmates kilograms upon kilograms of venison. He was not a hunter and we had no idea how he had gotten the venison, but the English missionaries didn't want to look a gift horse in the mouth and brought the meat back to our apartment. We fit what little we could in the freezer and left the rest sitting on the kitchen counter, then we went to bed.</p>
<p>We were unsupervised 19- and 20-year-olds and did not see a single problem in our plan.</p>
<p>The next morning, I woke up to one of the English missionaries yelling, "What in the world?! Guys, wake up! Come here! There's a river of blood!" He'd gone to the kitchen half-asleep in the morning and saw that the meat sitting on the counter had thawed and that <strong>A LOT</strong> of myoglobin had seeped through the packaging and pooled on the floor.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hospital-visit">Hospital visit<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#hospital-visit" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hospital visit" title="Direct link to Hospital visit">​</a></h4>
<p>Most people resented us when we knocked their doors unannounced or stopped them on the street. We only did it because we felt it was important; nobody likes inconveniencing others and being rejected dozens of times a day.</p>
<p>Consequently, we were constantly looking for better ways to find receptive people. One day, we decided to start calling members of our branch who hadn't been to church in a long time. Maybe they were ready to start attending church again and had family members or friends who'd be interested in having us over.</p>
<p>We found out that a lady from our branch was in hospital, awaiting an important surgery. "Is it OK if we pay you a visit to give you a blessing?," we asked her over the phone. She agreed, and we visited her that same day. Her boyfriend did not like us very much, but he warmed up to us as we continue to visit their family after she was discharged.</p>
<p>The last I heard was that, shortly after I left New Brunswick, they got married, he got baptized, and they were a happy family.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="v-days">V-days<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#v-days" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to V-days" title="Direct link to V-days">​</a></h4>
<p>Back then, missionaries could only communicate with people outside of their areas by snail mail (with very few exceptions). In New Brunswick, I received an unexpected letter from a childhood friend, who had moved away from Curitiba nearly a decade before.</p>
<p>Her name was Verónica, but everyone called her Vero. Vero's letters were tender and entertaining, and I did my best to reply in kind.</p>
<p>When she sent me her picture, I was struck. She was drop-dead gorgeous.</p>
<p>I was developing feelings for her, but we were told to "lock our hearts" as missionaries so we could focus on the work. That was hard to do, what with our teenage hormones going off.</p>
<p>So I made a decision. I would only read and reply to Vero's letters on Wednesdays, which was our mission's day off. Wednesdays were called <em>preparation days</em>, or "P-days" for short, but everybody knew that they were my special <strong>V-days</strong>.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-61b28f">
<p><a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/33?lang=eng&amp;id=p1#p1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2 Nephi 33:1</a>. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-one#user-content-fnref-1-61b28f" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>coelhoigor@gmail.com (Igor Coelho A. S. Marques)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3. Mission (Year 2)]]></title>
            <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two</link>
            <guid>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:02:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="long-branch">Long Branch<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#long-branch" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Long Branch" title="Direct link to Long Branch">​</a></h2>
<p>A year into my mission, I was transferred to Long Branch on the Jersey shore.</p>
<p>That area showed me the extent of wealth inequality in the US. We'd meet undocumented men who worked as day labourers and lived in cramped rooms with no beds or furniture of any kind. We'd meet children with rotten teeth and tattered clothing practically raising themselves on the street because it was better than being home with their parents.</p>
<p>Then we'd drive down Ocean Ave and gawk at the mansions in Deal.</p>
<p>One time, my companion and I were caught in an unexpected thunderstorm while we were out on the street. We stopped under an eave to wait out the storm. A few moments later, this happened:</p>
<ol>
<li>A minivan parked on the street.</li>
<li>A man got off the minivan.</li>
<li>He hurried to a house nearby and entered it.</li>
<li>He came out of the house with an umbrella.</li>
<li>He handed us the umbrella.</li>
<li>He got back in the minivan and drove off.</li>
</ol>
<p>That was one of the most random things that has ever happened to me.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="atlantic-city">Atlantic City<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#atlantic-city" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Atlantic City" title="Direct link to Atlantic City">​</a></h2>
<p>I spent my second winter in the mission in Atlantic City, NJ. Come Christmastime, we said yes to everyone who invited us for supper on Christmas eve. We went from home to home to home on a sort of holiday binge and ate a ridiculous amount of food that December 24<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ac-branch">AC branch<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#ac-branch" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AC branch" title="Direct link to AC branch">​</a></h3>
<p>We didn't have an actual church building in AC. Spanish-speaking members in the area attended a branch that rented a space in the city. This branch held two sacrament meetings each Sunday, one in the morning and one in the evening. No other congregation in the Church does this, as far as I'm aware. Ostensibly, they did this to accommodate the members' schedules, who had competing work shifts at the AC casinos.</p>
<p>It didn't really work out, though. Most people came in the morning. The attendance for the evening services was abysmal, and the few people who came consistently in the evening just took turns giving talks and saying the prayers. It was a little sad.</p>
<p>The AC Spanish branch no longer exists. It was moribund when I was there during the 2008 recession, and must have gotten worse when several casinos closed down in the mid 2010s. I imagine this downturn drove off the Spanish-speaking immigrants in the area, whom the casinos employed as cooks, housekeepers, busboys, etc. The pandemic and the rise of sports betting and online gambling in recent years must have sealed the deal.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="confrontation">Confrontation<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#confrontation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Confrontation" title="Direct link to Confrontation">​</a></h3>
<p>We were used to belligerent people. We were not shy about defending our beliefs when someone was hostile to us, but we tried to avoid confrontation as much as possible because it was not productive. It was a tug of war with no winners.</p>
<p>We lived by this verse in the Book of Mormon,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>He that hath the spirit of contention is not of [God], but is of the devil, who is the father of contention, and he stirreth up the hearts of men to contend with anger, one with another.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#user-content-fn-1-7a6928" id="user-content-fnref-1-7a6928" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When we sensed that people just wanted to argue with us, we tried to retreat diplomatically. If they weren't going to share our beliefs, at least we hoped they'd remember us as decent people. But some people trapped us before attacking us (verbally, mostly).</p>
<p>Whenever my companion and I were tired of working in AC, we took the train to Egg Harbor City and worked there. One of those days, a man didn't send us away after knocking on his door and talked to us on the doorstep. That was rare.</p>
<p>"Elder... Mar-KAY? Mar-KEE? What is that, French?," he asked me.</p>
<p>"Portuguese. You can call me Mar-KES. I'm Brazilian."</p>
<p>"Brazilian? You're white. Blue eyes. Where're your folks from?"</p>
<p>I got that all the time. People did not realize Brazil is a diverse country. But this man was not ignorant. I could tell he was baiting me.</p>
<p>"They're also Brazilian," I replied. "In fact, my ancestors have been in Brazil since the 1700s. And before that, Portugal. Pretty standard for Brazilians."</p>
<p>"Not at all. You're pure white. Not a hint of black or brown. You come from a lineage of untainted slave owners and Indian killers, don't you? Hundreds of years in Brazil and not one of your ancestors wanted to sleep with a black lady?"<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#user-content-fn-2-7a6928" id="user-content-fnref-2-7a6928" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup></p>
<p>I didn't know how to respond. The man was right, at least partially. I do have slave-owning ancestors. But that's just one branch of my family tree. I also have a freedwoman ancestor from the early 1800s in Minas Gerais. My maternal grandmother's maternal grandmother came from an indigenous group in southern Maranhão.</p>
<p>But there was no point in contradicting the man. He bid us go in, and we sat in his living room. We never refused an invitation to enter a home. He continued to be edgy and toy with us just to see how we would react. He was bored on a Saturday afternoon, and we were his entertainment.</p>
<p>"I used to be gay, you know. I know how you guys feel about gays," he said. The Church had been on the news recently for sponsoring ads in support of <a href="https://library.law.howard.edu/civilrightshistory/lgbtq/prop8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Proposition 8</a>, which banned same-sex marriage in California that year. "But I grew out of that," he continued. "As soon as I tried ladies, I realized I really, really liked them." He the described how he had met his wife, who was upstairs, in graphic detail.</p>
<p>I didn't feel threatened by that man, but I did feel icky after the visit. Thankfully, later that day we found a nice Honduran family and made baleadas with them. They were modest and kind and sharing a meal with them restored my spirit.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="princeton">Princeton<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#princeton" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Princeton" title="Direct link to Princeton">​</a></h2>
<p>My mission leaders sent me to Princeton, NJ, an English-speaking area, to finish my mission. Spring in Princeton was unreal. The streets were fragrant, abuzz with bumblebees, and dressed in bright colours.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="companionship-troubles">Companionship troubles<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#companionship-troubles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Companionship troubles" title="Direct link to Companionship troubles">​</a></h3>
<p>My time in Princeton was weird. On the one hand, I was at my boldest as a missionary. The apathy of the university community toward us somehow energized me, and I started to feel empowered by rejection. I walked upright and did not have a problem talking to anyone.</p>
<p>On the other hand, I hardly connected with anybody. My first companion there was terrible. He refused to talk to people and chewed me out openly in front of anyone. He'd been seeing a therapist, but the pressures of missionary work got to him and he ended up going home a few weeks later, six months before his release date.</p>
<p>The missionary that replaced him was lazy and petty, but not as mean. We worked less than we should and had zero success. With one exception.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="technically-i-taught-at-princeton">Technically, I taught at Princeton<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#technically-i-taught-at-princeton" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Technically, I taught at Princeton" title="Direct link to Technically, I taught at Princeton">​</a></h3>
<p>A woman in her twenties was receptive to our messages. She was was pursuing a graduate degree at Princeton and had become good friends with a classmate who was a member of our ward. I'm not sure if she had ulterior motives vis-à-vis her friend, but I don't think she did. She was bright and genuine. My companion and I shared our messages with her and her friend once a week in a classroom on campus. She eventually lost interest, and I still blame myself for that.</p>
<p>Missionaries say they are "trunky" when they feel indolent toward the end of their missions, i.e., their trunks are packed and they are fixated about going home. Regrets aside, I was never "trunky" in Princeton and continued to work hard until my last day on the field in late May 2009.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-7a6928">
<p><a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/11?lang=eng&amp;id=p29#p29" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">3 Nephi 11:29</a> <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#user-content-fnref-1-7a6928" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-2-7a6928">
<p>The way he spoke was ... much more <strong>colourful</strong> than how I feel comfortable writing. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/mission-year-two#user-content-fnref-2-7a6928" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>coelhoigor@gmail.com (Igor Coelho A. S. Marques)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[4. Long-distance relationship]]></title>
            <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship</link>
            <guid>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:03:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="in-person-v-days">In-person V-days<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#in-person-v-days" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to In-person V-days" title="Direct link to In-person V-days">​</a></h2>
<p>After I was honourably released from my mission, I met with <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/church/leader/richard-g-scott?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Elder Richard Scott</a>, a member of the <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/learn/quorum-of-the-twelve-apostles?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quorum of Twelve Apostles</a>. Among other things, he told me that my next priority should be finding an "eternal companion." My mind went to Vero.</p>
<p>I finished my mission in May 2009, four months before I had to resume my studies at BYU, and I chose to spend that time in Curitiba. Vero had broken up with her previous boyfriend some time before and agreed to come to Brazil to see if we were a good match.</p>
<p>We were. We clicked instantly. She smelled good and I liked the way she spoke Spanish. We had fun getting to know each other and going to Curitiba's tourist destinations. I even serenaded her with a song I'd written on the piano. When we were in line at a fast food joint, I hugged her from behind, she turned her face around, and we kissed for the first time. I still get butterflies in my stomach thinking about that moment.</p>
<p>When I felt shy about telling her something, I spelled out the words on the palms of her hand with my index finger, Helen Keller-style. After she'd been in Brazil for a few days, we found ourselves in the back of my parents' car on a long road trip. I asked her, "Will you be my girlfriend?," with my tactile writing system. She said no; she wanted me to "propose" out loud and in a more appropriate setting.</p>
<p>A few days later, I asked her again, out loud in a better place, and she said yes. We agreed to have a long-distance relationship while we were in university, and I promised to do my best to visit her in Chile at least once a year on my summer breaks.</p>
<p>My parents loved Vero. After she went back home, my father told me he'd support our relationship and covered the cost of an airfare to Chile so I could see her again before going to Provo. I met Vero's family and friends, and fell more in love with her.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="classical-89">Classical 89<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#classical-89" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Classical 89" title="Direct link to Classical 89">​</a></h2>
<p>When I finally returned to Provo, I landed a job interview at the university's classical music radio station, <a href="https://www.classical89.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Classical 89 (KBYU-FM)</a>. It was the perfect fit for me, a music major and classical music nerd.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="interview">Interview<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#interview" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Interview" title="Direct link to Interview">​</a></h3>
<p>The interview was a bit more intense than I expected. At one point, one of the interviewers asked me if I was able to tell the conductor and orchestra of a recording just by listening. No way. Not even nowadays. He said he could. It was not a weird power move; he was a nice guy and hoped to bond with me by nerding out together.</p>
<p>The interviewers wanted to make sure that:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was passionate about classical music.</li>
<li>I could write "my way out of a paper bag."</li>
<li>I had a good voice for radio.</li>
</ul>
<p>I checked the first two out of these three boxes; my accent and lack of experience got in the way of the third. Nevertheless, I got the job.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="job-duties">Job duties<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#job-duties" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Job duties" title="Direct link to Job duties">​</a></h3>
<p>The people who hired me at Classical 89 gave me the title of <em>assistant producer</em> and told me that that was not the position that I had applied for—that had gone to another young man—but that they had liked me and wanted to keep me because another student was going to graduate soon anyway.</p>
<p>My main tasks as an assistant producer were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Assist with the logistics of concert recordings</li>
<li>Edit and package interviews and live performances for the air</li>
<li>Support the full-time announcers in their shifts</li>
<li>Pre-record shifts that would air on weekday evenings and weekends</li>
</ul>
<p>I've always chosen my words carefully because I hated being misunderstood as a child. Working at Classical 89 helped me elevate that personality trait into communicative power. I learned a lot by reading aloud what I'd written and then revising it until it sounded good enough to say it on the air.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="crisis-of-self-awareness">Crisis of self-awareness<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#crisis-of-self-awareness" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Crisis of self-awareness" title="Direct link to Crisis of self-awareness">​</a></h3>
<p>One day, I checked out a portable Zoom recorder at work. Strangely, I noticed that the recorder's storage was almost full, even though everyone used to format the recorders before checking them in after using them. I listened to the recording to find out who had made it so I could ask for their permission to clear the memory and use the recorder for my project.</p>
<p>It was the young man who had gotten the position I had applied for. I'd been working with him for several months and I thought he was a nice guy. In the recording, he was interviewing his wife, as a joke.</p>
<p>Then, out of nowhere, he began to role-play as me.</p>
<p>He put on a thick accent and started acting stupid. In his role-play, he, or rather, <em>I</em> was courting his wife like a jackass while she refused my advances, laughing. I thought it was weird that she acted like she knew who I was, even though we'd never met. Was I the person that couple liked gossiping about? Were there other people who thought I was like that?</p>
<p>I didn't hear the whole thing. I paused the recording at some point because I was too perplexed to continue. Maybe that parody of me was a truer version of myself than the person I thought I was.</p>
<p>I considered how rare and fleeting self-awareness can be. In the years since, I have accepted self-awareness as one my life's most elusive goals, and made peace with the fact that I may never know who I really am, or who I appear to be to other people.</p>
<p>I was baffled by my co-worker's recording, but not offended. I've always enjoyed making people laugh, regardless of the reason. Incidentally, I wish I had saved that recording, but I think I deleted it right away.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="chile-2010">Chile 2010<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#chile-2010" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Chile 2010" title="Direct link to Chile 2010">​</a></h2>
<p>Vero had a friend from Chiguayante, her hometown, who had moved to Provo recently. I'd met her in Chile and thought she was great fun, so we met up once or twice that year. On Saturday, 27 February 2010, she called me in the morning.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="27f">27F<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#27f" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 27F" title="Direct link to 27F">​</a></h3>
<p>"Have you had any news from Vero?" Her voice wavered with a hint of desperation. "I can't get in touch with my family!"</p>
<p>"Why? What's wrong?"</p>
<p>"You haven't heard?"</p>
<p>"Heard what?"</p>
<p>"There's been a massive earthquake near Conce, one of the worst ones ever! And a tsunami, too. Phone, internet, nothing's working, so nobody knows if people there are OK." (She was right; that earthquake, nicknamed 27F, remains the eighth most intense seismic activity in recorded history.)</p>
<p>We commiserated with each other and tried calling, emailing, using social media, anything to reach the people we loved down there. Over the course of that weekend, she was able to talk to her family, and I got a call from Vero, who apparently had borrowed a satellite phone.</p>
<p>Vero told me that the earthquake had been vicious, that her family was OK, and that their home appeared to have suffered no structural damage. Life was complicated with severe aftershocks, looting, damaged roads, and a lack of services, but they were safe albeit traumatized and constantly on edge. She told me not to worry and that her family, neighbourhood, and Church ward were managing. Then she hung up.</p>
<p>Vero has fascinating stories about 27F, but they are hers to tell. On my end, all I could do was wait and hope for the best.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="world-cup">World Cup<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#world-cup" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to World Cup" title="Direct link to World Cup">​</a></h3>
<p>Chileans are proud of their resilience and the country soon resumed activities, even though many people continued to struggle for years with the after-effects of 27F.</p>
<p>When I visited Chile that summer (which was winter in the Southern Hemisphere), I was most impressed by the ruins of the <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edificio_Alto_R%C3%ADo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alto Río</a>, a 15-storey building near the Biobío river that broke in half and collapsed during the earthquake. An <a href="https://www.architectural-review.com/buildings/atanacio-soza-arquitectos-memorial-27f-a-potential-symbol-of-drastic-change" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">imposing but controversial memorial</a> was erected near the site of the Alto Río in 2013.</p>
<p>I also noticed that 27F had become a scapegoat for problems that clearly antedated it, so I started joking with Vero and blaming 27F for any inconvenience I encountered.</p>
<p>2010 was a World Cup year as well, and Chileans were excited about the prospects of their national team. The Chilean squad did very well in the tournament until they had to go against Brazil in the round of 16, at which point they were properly thrashed, 3-0. That could've caused some friction with my girlfriend, but she was as Brazilian as she was Chilean, and felt comfortable with whatever outcome of that match.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="year-3-at-byu">Year 3 at BYU<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#year-3-at-byu" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Year 3 at BYU" title="Direct link to Year 3 at BYU">​</a></h2>
<p>Fall 2010 marked the beginning of my third year in university. Academically, I was doing very well and had qualified for not one, but two simultaneous full-tuition bursaries.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alma">ALMA<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#alma" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ALMA" title="Direct link to ALMA">​</a></h3>
<p>Whenever I was not in class or at work, I spent most of my time in the <a href="https://music.byu.edu/facilities/electronic-facilities" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Advanced Lab for Music Applications</a> (ALMA) in BYU's Harris Fine Arts Center (HFAC). The ALMA had row after row of MIDI keyboards, each with a pair of headphones and a computer with all the music and audio apps I could want. The ALMA was located in a weird annex of the HFAC, away from most foot traffic, so it became a sort of sanctuary for me.</p>
<p>I thought back to my reticence about applying to BYU, and the ALMA made me feel grateful for my parents' insistence.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="move-to-orem">Move to Orem<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/long-distance-relationship#move-to-orem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Move to Orem" title="Direct link to Move to Orem">​</a></h3>
<p>In late 2010, my parents decided to spend a small fortune they had been saving to buy a condo in Orem near exit 273 of the I-15. It had high ceilings, three bedrooms, two bathrooms, and a nice balcony with a view of the Wasatch Mountains. It was a couple of blocks away from <a href="https://www.wincofoods.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WinCo</a>, my favourite grocery store ever, and about 5 km away from scenic Utah Lake.</p>
<p>That condo would be my home until 2015. I loved living there and never took it for granted.</p>
<p>As 2011 rolled around, life was going well. I was excelling in university, I loved my job and my condo, and I had all the support I needed to feel stable and happy. I talked to Vero every night, which was no replacement for us being <em>physically</em> together, but was enough to carry me over until the summer.</p>
<p>Still, I began to sense a new spectre nearby: my quarter-life crisis.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>coelhoigor@gmail.com (Igor Coelho A. S. Marques)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[5. Wedding]]></title>
            <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding</link>
            <guid>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:04:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="fear-of-failure">Fear of failure<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#fear-of-failure" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Fear of failure" title="Direct link to Fear of failure">​</a></h2>
<p>I turned 23 in '11 but did not feel like an adult. In my mind, I was still the wide-eyed teenager from Curitiba. I didn't have a clear artistic voice, my portfolio was unremarkable, and my creative output was mutating from "impressive for my age" to "not sure how this will help me get a job" and "maybe I should've become a diplomat like my dad wanted."</p>
<p>Meanwhile, my older cousins were finishing their undergraduate degrees and getting jobs, showing me what professional success looked like for international students like us. Their steps became my roadmap:</p>
<ol>
<li>Attend university with an <a href="https://www.uscis.gov/working-in-the-united-states/students-and-exchange-visitors/students-and-employment" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">F-1 student visa</a>.</li>
<li>Secure a job after graduation during the "practical training" grace period.</li>
<li>Have the employer sponsor the transition from F-1 to an <a href="https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/immigration/h1b" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">H-1B work visa</a>.</li>
<li>Live out the required number of years on H-1B to qualify for permanent residence, i.e., the <a href="https://www.uscis.gov/green-card" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Green Card</a>.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fn-1-79f473" id="user-content-fnref-1-79f473" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></li>
</ol>
<p>My cousins were also getting married and having babies by then. None of them considered going back to Brazil a viable option. They all wanted to make a life for their families in the US—as did I.</p>
<p>So, I set a couple of goals to help me accomplish it.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="goal-1-terminal-degree">Goal 1: Terminal degree<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#goal-1-terminal-degree" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Goal 1: Terminal degree" title="Direct link to Goal 1: Terminal degree">​</a></h3>
<p>All of the (living) composers I knew and admired had gone to grad school. No (living) composer I knew was making enough money to raise a family by writing music right out of undergrad. Ergo, I needed to get a master's and a doctorate in music composition if I were to get any good at it, and if I got good at it, I'd land a permanent, well-paying, visa-sponsoring job.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fn-2-79f473" id="user-content-fnref-2-79f473" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup></p>
<p>... right?</p>
<p>It'd take me much longer than my cousins to get to the coveted H-1B step, but eventually I'd get there, and then it would all have been worth it. I would've had my cake and eaten it too.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="goal-2-family">Goal 2: Family<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#goal-2-family" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Goal 2: Family" title="Direct link to Goal 2: Family">​</a></h3>
<p>Vero and I had always had a serious, marriage-oriented relationship. In 2010, we talked about our future and chose to get engaged. We spurned the custom that appeared to prevail in the US that a man should propose to a woman on one knee, seemingly out of the blue, with an expensive diamond ring and a specific short-term wedding date.</p>
<p>In Brazil, engagement was an agreement, not a surprise ultimatum one sprang on the other, and both the man and the woman wore plain gold bands when they got engaged—somewhat dear, but still a fraction of the price of the engagement rings people go into debt for in the US. The discussion that culminated in the decision to get married could happen in a specially romantic or significant place for the couple, but usually there were no theatrics involved. Engaged couples then invited their family and friends to a party to announce and celebrate their engagement, and remained engaged for up to a few years until the conditions were right to get married.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fn-3-79f473" id="user-content-fnref-3-79f473" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">3</a></sup></p>
<p>When I visited Vero in Chile in 2010, we got our wedding bands—courtesy of my maternal grandmother—and announced our engagement to our families and friends.</p>
<p>We thought it'd be a good idea to get married in December 2011. Vero would be done with university coursework and would need an just additional half year to undertake a mandatory practical internship. Incidentally, as an international student in the US, I could defer my studies for a half year, making me able to move to Chile and support her during her internship.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="concepción">Concepción<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#concepci%C3%B3n" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Concepción" title="Direct link to Concepción">​</a></h2>
<p>Vero and I got married in the church of the <a href="https://maps.churchofjesuschrist.org/wards/130354" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">University ward</a> in Concepción. The ceremony itself took place in the chapel and was officiated by a justice of the peace (JP). Vero had stressed to me how important it was to be punctual because Chilean JPs were notoriously impatient with delays, but she acted against her own advice and arrived half an hour late to our wedding. I was freaking out, but luckily our JP didn't seem to mind Vero's tardiness.</p>
<p>After we were married, the JP left and Vero and I went to the nearby campus of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Concepci%C3%B3n" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">University of Concepción</a>, her alma mater, to take pictures with a photographer. Meanwhile, our guests started on the appetizers in the church's cultural hall.</p>
<p>Our wedding reception was modest but plentiful and fun. Dozens of relatives and friends attended—including my parents, siblings, and an aunt that worked tirelessly that day to decorate the hall we held our reception in. We ate a delicious meal prepared by the catering business Vero worked for on weekends and danced until late that night.</p>
<p>After the reception, we travelled 500 km north to Santiago, where we were <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/temples/what-happens-in-a-temple-sealing?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sealed in the temple</a> the following day. This ordinance extended our civil marriage beyond death, and deepened our commitment to each other. Then we flew to Uruguay and spent our honeymoon in Punta del Este.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="first-apartment">First apartment<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#first-apartment" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to First apartment" title="Direct link to First apartment">​</a></h3>
<p>A week later, Vero and I were back in Concepción. We lived in a tiny one-bedroom apartment on Ongolmo, close to Paicaví and Carrera, a central area in the city with lots of young people like us. Nights were rough for me because our neighbours were loud and drunk people often argued and fought in front of our apartment building. Vero slept through it all.</p>
<p>As the seasons changed, we experienced some of the most terrifying windstorms I've ever seen. One time, I was walking back from church alone on Sunday when I heard a heart-stopping noise. A powerful gust had lifted a large corrugated zinc sheet from a building behind me and sent it dancing in the air, thundering with each flutter.</p>
<p>Another time, there was such an intense driving rain that water was spouting violently out of the rabbets of our apartment's windows. The putty on those windows was old and spotty, so I had an idea: stuff the rabbets with thin plastic bags, like the ones grocery stores used to give customers back then. Vero laughed and laughed, but it worked. It didn't look great, but it worked.</p>
<p>I still brag about the presence of mind I showed that day, and Vero still laughs. But I've never minded her laughing. I love to make her laugh more than anybody else.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="censo-2012">Censo 2012<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#censo-2012" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Censo 2012" title="Direct link to Censo 2012">​</a></h3>
<p>Before long, Vero settled in her routine doing her internship while I looked for a job. Money continued to be a pressing issue because we didn't have savings and Vero's internship didn't pay. I'd also been taught, for better or worse, that a man's worth depends on his work ethic and his ability to financially support his family. Since I was not studying, I had to work.</p>
<p>My first job in Concepción was at a radio station, selling ad space. I hated it and quit after my first paycheque.</p>
<p>Then, I learned about a well-paid, temporary gig for the government that aligned perfectly with our time frame. Chile was going to hold its <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Censo_chileno_de_2012" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">decennial census in 2012</a>, and they were looking for an army of census takers. I applied and mysteriously got the job, even though no one else we knew who had applied—and there were many in our age group—had been selected.</p>
<p>I <strong>loved</strong> working for the census. It was all of the fun parts of my mission minus the rejection and heartache. I walked the streets of Concepción 10 hours a day, going from home to home and interviewing people about their lives and families. I met people across the socioeconomic spectrum, from well-to-do traditional families to destitute squatters.</p>
<p>Being a census taker could be hilarious, too. Many people did not understand the questions we asked—or what the census itself even was, for that matter. This led to some confusion.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="material">Material<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#material" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Material" title="Direct link to Material">​</a></h4>
<p>I had to ask people what their residences were made of. Most people had no idea. Some people answered "material," which is as vague and obvious in Spanish as it is in English. They said it with such confidence, too. I soon learned that some old-timers used "material" in opposition to wood, so it basically meant brick and mortar (for houses) or reinforced concrete (for apartment buildings).</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="being-indigenous">Being indigenous<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#being-indigenous" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Being indigenous" title="Direct link to Being indigenous">​</a></h4>
<p>When people declared they were indigenous, the mandatory follow-up question was about their ethnic group. For indigenous people, the answer was straightforward. Those who self-identified as indigenous but didn't have strong ties with a particular group were generally stumped. Some walked back and said they weren't actually indigenous. Others doubled down and said that all Chileans should consider themselves indigenous and picked the <a href="https://www.britannica.com/topic/Mapuche" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mapuche</a> as their ethnic group because they represented anti-colonial resistance.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="polyglots">Polyglots<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#polyglots" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Polyglots" title="Direct link to Polyglots">​</a></h4>
<p>The census asked people about the languages they spoke. It was not uncommon for upper middle-class parents to proudly state that their children spoke two, three, four languages. It was not just parental pride; it was a matter of social prestige and a return of their investment.</p>
<p>In Chile, private K-12 schools were the norm for middle-class families. This included lower middle-class families, who prioritized private education for their children as soon as they could afford it. Some private schools for the upper social classes in Concepción distinguished themselves from the rest by offering foreign-language immersion programs and calling themselves the "British" or the "French" or the "Arabic" school. This fed into people's strong pro-foreigner (especially pro-European) bias.</p>
<p>I'd spoken with Chileans in English and had good reason to doubt those kids spoke all of those languages fluently, but I put down whatever their parents told me.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="audífono">Audífono<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#aud%C3%ADfono" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Audífono" title="Direct link to Audífono">​</a></h4>
<p>The word for "hearing aid" in Spanish is <em>audífono</em>, which is the same word for "headphones." One of the questions I had to ask was,</p>
<p><em>"Do you have difficulty hearing, even with a</em> hearing aid <em>on?"</em></p>
<p>Some young people who didn't know what a hearing aid was thought I was asking them,</p>
<p><em>"Do you have difficulty hearing when you have</em> headphones <em>on?"</em></p>
<p>"Well, yes," one young man told me. "I like to listen to loud music on my iPod and can't hear anything when I've got my headphones on."</p>
<p>I wasn't supposed to question people's answers and had to record exactly what they said, but  whenever this misunderstanding happened, I'd clarify what type of <em>audífono</em> I was referring to.</p>
<p>"OK, then no," they amended.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="relation">Relation<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#relation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Relation" title="Direct link to Relation">​</a></h4>
<p>The census required us to determine how people were related to the head of household. The question we had to ask about each person was something like,</p>
<p><em>"Cuál es su relación con el jefe de hogar?"</em></p>
<p>Which means,</p>
<p><em>"How are you and the head of household related?</em></p>
<p>Possible answers included: self, spouse, child, parent, etc. However, because <em>relación</em> can mean "relationship" in addition to "relation" (as in degree of kinship), what some people heard was,</p>
<p><em>"What is your relationship with the head of household like?</em></p>
<p>Then they'd start going off about their marital problems and parenting challenges, which people somehow thought the census would like to record.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="can-i-go-now">Can I go now?<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#can-i-go-now" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Can I go now?" title="Direct link to Can I go now?">​</a></h2>
<p>After the census ended,<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fn-4-79f473" id="user-content-fnref-4-79f473" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">4</a></sup> I felt empty. I could only watch so much <em>The Office</em> (US) and play so much <em>Batman: Arkham City</em> on my PlayStation before I felt an itch to resume "my life" in Orem, as selfish as that was.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-79f473">
<p>Some of my cousins were able to speedrun this process by marrying US citizens. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fnref-1-79f473" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-2-79f473">
<p>I knew that composers-slash-producers who worked for mass media didn't need a terminal degree, but I didn't want go into that. Even though I had gotten into music composition because I wanted to write <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/from-curitiba-to-provo#video-game-music">music for video games</a>, my time at BYU convinced me that a career in academia would give me the most freedom to pursue my crazy ideas. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fnref-2-79f473" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-3-79f473">
<p>Getting engaged in Chile was similar enough. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fnref-3-79f473" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-4-79f473">
<p>The 2012 census in Chile was <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Censo_chileno_de_2012#Controversias" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">controversial and likely fraudulent</a>, and had to be re-taken five years later. I have zero regrets about how I performed my duties, but apparently there were systemic issues with the whole process. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/wedding#user-content-fnref-4-79f473" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 4" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>coelhoigor@gmail.com (Igor Coelho A. S. Marques)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[6. Graduation (BYU)]]></title>
            <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu</link>
            <guid>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:05:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="back-in-orem">Back in Orem<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#back-in-orem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Back in Orem" title="Direct link to Back in Orem">​</a></h2>
<p>In addition to my university courses, I had a lot to do in the fall of '12:</p>
<ul>
<li>Polish my portfolio and resume</li>
<li>Take the <a href="https://www.ets.org/gre/test-takers.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Graduate Records Examination</a></li>
<li>Apply to graduate programs in several universities</li>
<li>Write my capstone project</li>
</ul>
<p>But I should've stayed a little longer in Concepción.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="veros-graduation">Vero's graduation<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#veros-graduation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Vero's graduation" title="Direct link to Vero's graduation">​</a></h3>
<p>I returned to the US in late July 2012 to prepare for my classes and to get everything in order for Vero to come after her convocation ceremony in mid-September.</p>
<p>I regret doing it that way. I could've arranged an accommodation to miss the first few weeks of classes at BYU to attend Vero's graduation. Even in the worst case scenario, I could've survived a few bad marks.</p>
<p>This was my first big lapse of judgment as a husband. Being a good and loving husband has been a learning process for me. I've never been abusive or mean, but I wasn't very affectionate at that stage, and I didn't prioritize my wife like I should have.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="salary-negotiation">Salary negotiation<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#salary-negotiation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Salary negotiation" title="Direct link to Salary negotiation">​</a></h3>
<p>Shortly after I went back to work at <a href="https://www.classical89.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Classical 89</a>, a cousin of mine helped me land a job offer at the <a href="https://provo.mtc.byu.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MTC</a> to be a Portuguese-language tutor. I loved working at Classical 89 and didn't want to leave, but I also could not refuse work that paid 35% more than what I earned at the time. Especially now that there were two mouths to feed.</p>
<p>I went to see my boss at the radio station to hand in my notice. I was transparent with him and he asked me, "If we match what they'll pay you at the MTC, will you stay?" Part of me hoped for this outcome, but I honestly didn't think I'd be able to use my MTC job offer as leverage to negotiate a significant raise; I thought the station simply could not afford to pay me any more than they did. When my boss suggested the raise, I felt relieved and grateful, and I happily stayed at Classical 89 until my graduation.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="veros-esl-classes">Vero's ESL classes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#veros-esl-classes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Vero's ESL classes" title="Direct link to Vero's ESL classes">​</a></h3>
<p>When Vero arrived in the US, her English was good but not yet fluent, so she enrolled in BYU's <a href="https://elc.byu.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">English Language Center</a> (ELC) and studied English full-time from January-April 2013. During this period, her immigration status changed from F-2 (spouse of an international student) to F-1 (international student), which meant she could now obtain a Social Security Number and a driver's licence, and work part-time on campus like me.</p>
<p>In theory, ELC students could work any job on campus. In practice, the vast majority of them worked custodian jobs that required little to no communication skills, and that's what Vero did as well. She cleaned office spaces in the Wilkinson Center from 4-8 am on weekdays before attending classes. It was a far cry from being a dental surgeon in Chile, but we could use the money and Vero was a good sport about it.</p>
<p>A lot of what I did at Classical 89 by that point was pre-recorded, so I arranged with my supervisor to work a very early shift like Vero. My voice sounded nice and deep at that time of day, too.</p>
<p>Waking up that early was hard, though. Both of us had attended <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/si/seminary?lang=eng" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">early-morning seminary</a> every day at 6 am as teenagers, but our condo was located more than 15 km northwest of campus and we had to wake up at about 3:15 am to shower, get ready for the day, and get to work on time.</p>
<p>One thing made our commutes easier. As we drove down Canyon Rd and then 900 E in Provo and got closer and closer to the Wasatch Mountains, we often saw groups of white-tailed deer grazing on people's lawns and even on the campus greens. It was magical. They never dared coming down from the mountains after sunrise.</p>
<p>I kept hoping we'd run into a cougar, which is BYU's mascot, either on our commutes or when we explored the trails in Rock Canyon, but we never did.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="one-quarter-century-down">One quarter century down<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#one-quarter-century-down" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to One quarter century down" title="Direct link to One quarter century down">​</a></h2>
<p>When I turned 25 in the spring of '13, I'd been married for a year and a half and had been accepted to the master's program in <a href="https://music.utah.edu/students/programs-degrees.php#comp" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">music composition at the University of Utah</a> (the U). They offered me a full-tuition scholarship and a graduate assistantship that paid more I had ever earned—a low bar to clear, but nice anyway.</p>
<p>I went on to graduate <em>cum laude</em> from BYU, and felt that I had become a seasoned radio producer after working at Classical 89 for nearly four years.</p>
<p>I no longer saw myself as a kid. I was an adult. Life was going according to plan, and I grew confident. I still felt underdeveloped as a composer, but I was hopeful I'd achieve the artistic maturity I sought in grad school.</p>
<p>So, Vero and I agreed: it was time for a baby.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="first-pregnancy">First pregnancy<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#first-pregnancy" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to First pregnancy" title="Direct link to First pregnancy">​</a></h3>
<p>Vero became pregnant with our first son, Samuel, when we were in Concepción, right before my master's started. I returned to the US before her to "prepare everything"—the excuse I used to leave Chile and selfishly resume "my life," again—while she had a stopover in Curitiba. We knew she'd been pregnant for about six weeks, so my mother took her for an ultrasound in Curitiba, and they heard Samuel's heartbeat for the first time.</p>
<p>We did not have health insurance in the US, so we signed up for prenatal care at a community health centre in Provo that offered sliding fee discounts for low-income people like us. The care Vero received at this clinic was not excellent and ultimately led to complications that caused Samuel to have a difficult premature birth.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="year-1-at-the-u">Year 1 at the U<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#year-1-at-the-u" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Year 1 at the U" title="Direct link to Year 1 at the U">​</a></h3>
<p>Vero and I chose not to move when the U accepted my application. We continued to live in the Orem condo my parents owned so we could save rent money. Our family was growing, after all. We also saved on gas because the U gave me a public transit pass, and that's what I used to travel the 65 km each way to go to campus.</p>
<p>My course schedule at the U was lighter than in my undergrad and my responsibilities as a grad assistant were flexible, so I didn't have to go to campus every day. When I did, Vero drove me to the Orem train station to take the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FrontRunner" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">FrontRunner</a> north to Murray Central, where I switched to the campus-bound <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TRAX_(light_rail)#Lines_and_stations" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Red Line TRAX</a>. It took me nearly two hours to go from home to campus or vice-versa.</p>
<p>I rarely drove myself to campus. It was twice as fast as public transit, but it left Vero stranded at home and was less comfortable and productive than riding the trains.</p>
<p>The FrontRunner had desks with eletrical outlets, and I could usually find one to sit at and play <em>Civilization V</em>, compose, or do some homework. When I switched to the TRAX, I liked reading books on my Kindle and listening to Ricky Gervais's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ricky_Gervais#Radio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcasts and old Xfm episodes</a> with Stephen Merchant and Karl Pilkington. I got hooked on their brand of humour and consumed everything else I discovered by them, like the animated HBO show, <em>An Idiot Abroad</em>, and <em>Derek</em>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="painful-to-read">"Painful to read"<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#painful-to-read" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to &quot;Painful to read&quot;" title="Direct link to &quot;Painful to read&quot;">​</a></h3>
<p>I got along well with my composition instructor at the U, <a href="https://morrisrosenzweig.com/bio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Morris Rosenzweig</a>. He was incredibly talented and clear-minded, and had the personality of a lovable grouchy old man, always kvetching about this or that. He held me in high regard, higher than I deserved.</p>
<p>I wanted to understand what made him tick. I interviewed him about his creative process and his daily routine, and wrote a paper about him, which I then submitted to <a href="https://www.perspectivesofnewmusic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Perspectives of New Music</em></a>.</p>
<p>I had to become a published researcher if I were to succeed in academia, and at almost 26 years of age, I needed to do it sooner rather than later. <em>Perspectives</em> is the go-to academic journal in the field of contemporary music in the US, but I'd gotten an A in the paper in my research methods course, so I figure I had a chance.</p>
<p>I got a scathing response from <em>Perspectives</em>. One reviewer wrote, and I paraphrase, "I hope it was less painful for Rosenzweig to sit through the interviews with this writer than it was for me to read this horrible paper."</p>
<p>I still have the email from <em>Perspectives</em> but I can't bring myself to open the attachment with the reviewers' comments, even after all these years. It was the lowest blow to my self-esteem to date. It's not like I didn't know rejection, either; rejection had been my daily bread as a missionary and a constant companion in my undergrad when I applied to competitions, new music festivals, and grad school programs. But this email from <em>Perspectives</em> was particularly scarring.<sup><a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#user-content-fn-1-d8d3cc" id="user-content-fnref-1-d8d3cc" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="water-breaking">Water breaking<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#water-breaking" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Water breaking" title="Direct link to Water breaking">​</a></h2>
<p>One night in the winter of '14, Vero started having frequent and powerful contractions. She was scared, but I assured her that they were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Braxton_Hicks_contractions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Braxton Hicks contractions</a>, and told her to go back to sleep.</p>
<p>Then, her water broke. She was officially in labour.</p>
<p>It was a nightmare. The baby had been suffering from intrauterine growth restriction and, at 35 weeks of pregnancy, he was not ready to be born. It was happening too soon.</p>
<p>We went down the three flights of stairs from our condo in quick spurts between Vero's contractions, got in our natural gas Honda Civic, and zoomed as fast as we could to the Utah Valley Hospital in Provo. It was the longest and loudest 15-minute car ride of my life.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-d8d3cc">
<p>It's hard to write this and not feel a deep insecurity bubbling up from that trauma. I hope the love of the people I've written this for, my family and friends, will help them see past my shortcomings. <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/graduation-byu#user-content-fnref-1-d8d3cc" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>coelhoigor@gmail.com (Igor Coelho A. S. Marques)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[7. Samuel]]></title>
            <link>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel</link>
            <guid>https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:06:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my resume and portfolio in different areas of this site.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a memoir of my adult life. You can find my <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/resume/intro">resume</a> and <a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/docs/portfolio/intro">portfolio</a> in different areas of this site.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="samuels-birth">Samuel's birth<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#samuels-birth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Samuel's birth" title="Direct link to Samuel's birth">​</a></h2>
<p>When we made it to hospital, a security guard rushed Vero in a wheelchair to her delivery room while I parked the car. I made my way up to Vero's room soon thereafter and saw hospital staffers hooking her up to medical equipment and asking all sorts of questions. They told us that Vero was well dilated and too far along the labour process to have an epidural, and that she was going to deliver the baby without anesthetics.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hard-delivery">Hard delivery<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#hard-delivery" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hard delivery" title="Direct link to Hard delivery">​</a></h3>
<p>Within minutes, the intervals between Vero's contractions reached a critical frequency and nurses and doctors swarmed around her and told her to push.</p>
<p>It didn't take long. After a few pushes, Samuel was born, but there was no crying. He was lifeless like a rag doll and his skin was purple-ish. A doctor moved him to a corner of the delivery room while I kept repeating to myself, "Something's wrong, something's wrong, something's wrong." My hands were shaking and I began to rock my body and cry. This must have lasted no more than a minute. I was about to collapse when the doctor who had been tending to Samuel managed to resuscitate him.</p>
<p>Then they took him away. What happened?</p>
<p>I was relieved that Samuel had survived his traumatic birth, but I could not shake the thought that he may have endured permanent neurological damage. I started freaking out again when a nurse handed me a drink.</p>
<p>They told me it was just orange juice. I think they might have spiked it with some benzodiazepine but could not disclose it. They must have been used to dealing with weak dads like me. Whatever the liquid was, I calmed down instantly after drinking it and asked Vero if she'd be OK with me going to check on Samuel in the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU).</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nicu-stay">NICU stay<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#nicu-stay" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to NICU stay" title="Direct link to NICU stay">​</a></h3>
<p>The doctor put Samuel in an incubator, inserted an intravenous drip on a vein on his head, and connected him to respiratory support. I was overwhelmed with love and concern for him. He was tiny, even for preemies, and looked hurt and emaciated.</p>
<p>The doctor told me that Samuel was stable and was going to keep getting better every day. I spent some more time there next to the incubator, then went back to Vero's room to report and rest.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="growth">Growth<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#growth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Growth" title="Direct link to Growth">​</a></h4>
<p>Samuel spent almost three weeks in the NICU. The hospital wanted to keep him there until he grew enough to fit safely and comfortably in a baby car seat. The doctor got Samuel off the ventilator a day after he was born, but the nurses kept tracking his oxygen level during his entire stay; I can still hear the machine beeping each time it dropped below 90% before going back to normal a few moments later.</p>
<p>Vero and I were so worried about his weight that we meticulously measured how many millilitres of milk she pumped each time, how many millilitres he drank, and how many grams he grew each time the nurses weighed him. We noticed that his growth was slow and irregular, but at least he was growing.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="waiting">Waiting<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#waiting" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Waiting" title="Direct link to Waiting">​</a></h4>
<p>Samuel's first week in the NICU coincided with spring break at the U, so I was able to be with him and Vero without interruptions. When classes and work resumed for me, my mother-in-law arrived in the US and filled in for me in the NICU, though I still visited the hospital whenever I could.</p>
<p>When Samuel slept, I kept Vero company and read books. On Sunday evenings, I liked to watch Neil deGrasse Tyson's <em>Cosmos: A Spacetime Odyssey</em> in the hospital's breakroom, which premiered that year.</p>
<p>When we had to go home after visiting hours, Vero would spend her nights looking at pictures and videos we had taken of Samuel in her cellphone. The nurses had told her that doing that would help with her milk production and her emotional well-being.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="finally-home">Finally home<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#finally-home" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Finally home" title="Direct link to Finally home">​</a></h2>
<p>After 18 days in the NICU, the hospital staff asked us to put Samuel in his car seat and leave him there for a while. They observed him and concluded that he was ready to go home.</p>
<p>It was the beginning of spring, and we dressed Samuel with a cute teddy bear outfit when we first brought him home. I drove very, very slowly on our way back from hospital. When we arrived in our condo, we were all tired but relieved and thankful.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="sleeping-issues">Sleeping issues<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#sleeping-issues" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Sleeping issues" title="Direct link to Sleeping issues">​</a></h3>
<p>As Samuel outgrew his bassinet and switched to a crib, he became fussy about sleeping. He had to be rocked for 10-30 minutes in the dark to the sound of white noise to fall asleep. Then, I'd look at his eyelids to figure out when he had entered rapid eye movement sleep; that was the sign that he could be transferred to his crib.</p>
<p>But I had to do it <strong>very</strong> carefully. Any sudden move, noise, or light, and Samuel would jolt awake, forcing me to repeat the whole process again. I learned to do a whole choreography that involved slowly sliding my arms from under his body and then waiting next to his crib for a few minutes to make sure he would not wake up when I tiptoed backward to the door of his room.</p>
<p>As far as nights were concerned, Vero and I had a plan. When Samuel woke up:</p>
<ol>
<li>I picked him up and brought him to Vero, who stayed in bed.</li>
<li>Vero breastfed him and changed his diaper.</li>
<li>I put him back to sleep in his crib.</li>
</ol>
<p>I think it was a good division of labour, but it was brutal on both of us.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="mental-health-issues">Mental health issues<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#mental-health-issues" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Mental health issues" title="Direct link to Mental health issues">​</a></h3>
<p>After my mother-in-law and my mother went back to their respectives homes, our sleep deprivation intensified the effects of Vero's hormonal changes and her sense of isolation and triggered a post-partum depression that went undiagnosed and untreated.</p>
<p>She felt trapped, abandoned, left behind. She watched her colleagues in Chile advance in their careers while she lost all hope in hers. She often cried, complained, and lashed out at me, despite my best efforts to ease her burden: I helped with Samuel; I did chores; I took our family on outings. But nothing seemed to have more than a temporary effect on her disposition. I was not able to make her laugh like before.</p>
<p>Her suffering got to me, and I began to break, too. No difficulty I had ever experienced before could compare to the agony I felt then. I've never fully recovered from that time, and I suspect that neither has Vero.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="love-above-all">Love above all<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#love-above-all" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Love above all" title="Direct link to Love above all">​</a></h3>
<p>In spite of our hardships, I fell in love with Samuel more and more each day.</p>
<p>I didn't know I was capable of loving so deeply and intensely. He imbued my life with purpose and adjusted my priorities. My studies, my career, my ego, nothing else seemed to matter too much in comparison to my son's (and my wife's) welfare and happiness.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="back-to-the-u">Back to the U<a href="https://igorcasmarques.github.io/my-story/samuel#back-to-the-u" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Back to the U" title="Direct link to Back to the U">​</a></h2>
<p>By the fall of '14, Vero's diligent breastfeeding and mothering had helped Samuel become a healthy, happy, and plump baby boy with no apparent sequelae of his complicated birth. He was still small, but Samuel's pediatrician told us that this was not a problem per se. After all, I'm a short man myself.</p>
<p>I was afraid Vero would have a hard time when I went back to school, but a visit from her older sister and two close friends from Chiguayante in October propped her spirit. After they were gone, we had Thanksgiving and Christmas with my cousins and their families to look forward to. Fun things would happen again; we just had to be patient.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, I continued to work hard on my master's degree. I taught university courses in music theory, sight singing, and dictation to 1<sup>st</sup>- and 2<sup>nd</sup>-year music majors at the U. I wrote my thesis project and helped coordinate the logistics of two new music ensembles.</p>
<p>I also applied to 10 different doctoral programs, all outside of Utah. I thought that my family needed a change of scenery in 2015.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>coelhoigor@gmail.com (Igor Coelho A. S. Marques)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>